<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A bloody Irish almanack, or, Rebellious and bloody Ireland, discovered in some notes extracted out of an almanack, printed at Waterford in Ireland for this yeare 1646. Whereunto are annexed some astrologicall observations upon a conjunction of the two malignant planets Saturne and Mars in the midle of the signe Taurus the horroscope of Ireland, upon Friday the 12. of Juue [sic] this yeare 1646. with memorable prædictions and occurrences therein. By John Booker.</title>
            <author>Booker, John, 1603-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3723A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113488</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113488)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A bloody Irish almanack, or, Rebellious and bloody Ireland, discovered in some notes extracted out of an almanack, printed at Waterford in Ireland for this yeare 1646. Whereunto are annexed some astrologicall observations upon a conjunction of the two malignant planets Saturne and Mars in the midle of the signe Taurus the horroscope of Ireland, upon Friday the 12. of Juue [sic] this yeare 1646. with memorable prædictions and occurrences therein. By John Booker.</title>
                  <author>Booker, John, 1603-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 57 [i.e. 59], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for John Partridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears "The explanation of the frontispeece", i.e. the title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Pages 57-59 misnumbered 58, 59, 57.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March: 18 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:113488:1"/>
            <head>The Explanation of the <hi>Frontiſpeece.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>MArke and behold yee bloudy <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation</l>
            <l>This Heavenly Figure; where my contemplation</l>
            <l>Hath beene implyoyed: Your horrid deedes, mee thought</l>
            <l>Would into queſtion in ſhort time be brought.</l>
            <l>Bloud cries for Bloud: mee thinks I feare each houre</l>
            <l>God will his vengeance on that Iſland powre.</l>
            <l>See <hi>Meger, Palefac'd, Saturne,</hi> Furious <hi>Mars,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <hi>Taurus, Irelands</hi> Signe, moſt diſmall Starres,</l>
            <l>By God appointed; for to doe his will.</l>
            <l>Fire, Famine, Sword, the Plague: of bloud their fill</l>
            <l>Shalbe their portion: <hi>Phalaris</hi> did frame</l>
            <l>A brazen Bull, But when the burning flame</l>
            <l>Had heate the Engine, He himſelfe firſt felt</l>
            <l>The cruell torments, which he would have dealt</l>
            <l>To others: <hi>Irelands</hi> caſe is farre more worſe</l>
            <l>The children yet unborne that folke will curſe.</l>
            <l>Though <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> The <hi>Pope,</hi> that man of ſin</l>
            <l>With his adherents you to ayde begin.</l>
            <l>And bring you ſuccour, Vengeance cries aloud</l>
            <l>Tis heap'd as raine into a fearefull cloud,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe that God reſtraine Heavens menaceing</l>
            <l>This ſad poſition will your ruine bring.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113488:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BLOODY <hi>IRISH</hi> ALMANACK, OR, Rebellious and Bloody IRELAND, Diſcovered in ſome Notes Extracted out of an ALMANACK, Printed at <hi>Waterford</hi> in IRELAND For this Yeare 1646.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut depicting astrologicall signs and figures</figDesc>
               <head>East South West North</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Whereunto are annexed ſome Aſtrologicall Obſervations upon a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the two <hi>Malignant</hi> Planets SATVRNE and MARS in the midle of the Signe TAVRVS the <hi>Horroſcope</hi> of IRELAND, Upon <hi>Friday</hi> the 12. of <hi>June</hi> this Yeare 1646. with memorable <hi>Praedictions</hi> and <hi>Occurrences</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>By JOHN BOOKER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>InenarranDVs DeVs est operIbVs sVIs, qVI transfere regna atqVè eXCIDIt ea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for JOHN PARTRIDGE, 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113488:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113488:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <p>BEing for ſome yeares late paſt publikely imployed on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Common-wealth of this Kingdome, I could not attend my Study of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> with that earneſtneſſe and paines I deſired, or with that former induſtry I for many years had under gon; and indeed I was almoſt diſcouraged in proſecuting the Writing of my Annuall <hi>Prognoſtick,</hi> when as in Licenſing the ſame, half my Aſtrology or what was moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the preſent times was moſt maliciouſly expunged, ſo that I ever appeared a lame &amp; deficient Perſon, ambiguous, and not eaſily to be apprehended: the fault not being mine, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to benefite my Native Country, but thoſe peeviſh Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Chaplaines who had ſole Licence either to permit, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anull my Writings.</p>
            <p>But the errors of that miſty Faction being now by divine Providence cleared, and liberty given by the Noble Parliament now reſident at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for advance of any humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; I have aſſumed liberty to appeare againe in the World (not in an <hi>Almanack,</hi> the leaſt thing I ever intended) but in a notable and eminent way of Prediction upon the famous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the two Malevolent Planets <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars;</hi> I am herein much incouraged by thoſe Labours of my Friend Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> not onely Printed in theſe times, but made more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable in the ſucceſſe I have obſerved hath followed his Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall Predictions: a few of which I will repeate that the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided in fancy againſt Aſtrology may not be deſtitute of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient teſtimony in his onely Writings of the verity of that Art, by which Art at this time I write the enſuing Diſcourſe. I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his <hi>Anglicus 1644,</hi> and ſhall relate ſome Obſervations out of his Propheticall <hi>Merlin,</hi> Printed <hi>1644.</hi> See fol. <hi>43</hi> upon his Judgement of the Comet <hi>1618.</hi> In <hi>1645</hi> let thoſe Princes that live neare the <hi>Mordway Tartar</hi> looke to themſelves, &amp;c. Is
<pb facs="tcp:113488:3"/> not the Kingdome of <hi>China</hi> bordering thereon almoſt deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſudden attempt of the <hi>Tartar 1645.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we will come home to <hi>England,</hi> See fol. <hi>98,</hi> and ſo it may be hoped towards the later end of <hi>1645</hi> we ſhall have great likelihoode of being in a better condition then now we are in: we were in a ſad condition when he wrote that Booke in <hi>1644.</hi> but in <hi>Decemb. 1645,</hi> the whole Kingdome knowes the words exactly verified, by the continuall ſucceſſes of our Parliaments Generall, and the ineſtimable loſſes of his Majeſtie and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers. Againe in the ſame fol. In <hi>1646</hi> all the Planets except <hi>Mercury</hi> ſaluting each other with one benevolent aſpect or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do moſt undoubtedly declare, that the miſery of the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Engliſh</hi> do draw neere to a period: and this is like to be ſo. See againe fol. <hi>100.</hi> Indeede in <hi>1646 Jupiter</hi> in the <hi>Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Mundi</hi> being in the aſcendant, &amp;c. Matters are not yet ripe and perfectly ſetled, yet better then formerly; ſome Prince ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fled or captivated, &amp;c. whether things are not farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and yet not rightly ſetled, and whether of late the Prince miſſed not of being captivated, but ſince is fled the Kingdome; we all know: Let who will pleaſe examine his whole Diſcourſe upon the conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> there in that Booke handled, and they ſhall ſee <hi>Aſtrology</hi> is not either vain or an unneceſſary Study.</p>
            <p>Let us obſerve ſome paſſages in his <hi>Starry Meſſenger</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed <hi>12 June 1645</hi> fol. <hi>23</hi> in his Premonition to Princes: <hi>Your Generalls ſhall quake and tremble and prove men of no courage, &amp;c.</hi> Hath not Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> fulfilled this, &amp;c. at the delivery of <hi>Briſtoll, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>Your confederates ſhall faile in reall performances;</hi> Obſerve the good hand of God, not any man of his Majeſties Friends hath ſupported him with a man or money ſince that Prediction, no not the beloved <hi>Iriſh Catholicks.</hi> In the ſame fol. <hi>Your Children ſhall wander as baniſhed people all over the world.</hi> How like this may be truth, let all wiſe men judge for Prince <hi>Charles</hi> is fled, and ſo may the reſt for ought I know.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113488:3"/>
            <p>Againe <hi>fol. 43.</hi> in anſwer to that Bifronted Buſſard <hi>Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> he ſayth it upon that oppoſition of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Septemb:</hi> we knock not our enemies ſoundly, God is angrie with us. I thinke we baſtinadoed them ſoundly neere that time at <hi>Sherburne,</hi> and at <hi>Rowten</hi> more. So that it appeares as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> wrote, God is not or was angry with us. But in his Poſtſcript of his Starry Meſſenger in anſwer to lying <hi>Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who publiſhed the Kings March from <hi>Oxford</hi> on the laſt ſide, publiſhed the ſame the <hi>12</hi> of <hi>June</hi> there are his words <hi>verbatim.</hi> But let me tell you, ſuch ſhall be our victories before the time limited by you be halfe come, viz. <hi>Novemb. 1645</hi>) that me thinks I heare the many curſed oathes the Dam-boyes ſpue out both againſt God &amp; man. Oh what ſculking ſneaking, running into Corners, mouſe-holes, ſawpits, Cunny-berries, toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and tumbling the ungodly out of one Country into another: doe I foreſee: face ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut Gentlemen ſayes one for our honour, as you did at <hi>Newberry,</hi> that is with a good paire of heeles, or alls loſt I ſay: Oh the way to <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> from thence to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter</hi> then into <hi>Cornwall,</hi> thence into a ſaſe harbour, if any can be found for Malignants. Gods Providence hath made thoſe words true, for d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d we not firſt take <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguer <hi>Exceter,</hi> and now this preſent <hi>March</hi> have we not in <hi>Cornwall</hi> unhorſed theſe pure Swaſh-buckling Cavaliers, ſo that now they may ſee theſe words to their ſhame and Gods glory fulfilled. But I am tedious, although no neede is thereof: let any indifferent man, judge on Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> Obſervations in this preſent March <hi>1646.</hi> He ſaith: the firſt weeke, Newes from ſeverall quarters, and ſome towne or fort ſurrendred, ſo we had, the ſurrender of <hi>Aſhby,</hi> and the town of <hi>Torrington</hi> Then he proceds: ſome propoſition from our weather beaten e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Weſtward. Is not this true in the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> his ſurrender of <hi>2000</hi> horſe upon modeſt propoſitions. Againe,
<pb facs="tcp:113488:4"/> his Majeſty ſtands amazed: who thinks leſſe then ſo, when he ſees all is like to be loſt. <hi>Here's ſtrugling ſaith he;</hi> this we in <hi>London</hi> know to be true. <hi>Againe, Three dayes promiſe our enemies ſucceſſe, but God may blinde their eyes to make uſe of none, that is, neither eyes nor time.</hi> The poore fellowes were in <hi>Abington, 2</hi> March: but were haſtily and valiantly thruſt out by the valour of the Garriſons; this was one of their promiſing dayes. In the ſecond weeke of March they attempted it againe, but to no purpoſe; the ſame weeke they miſſed our Convoy of <hi>20000</hi> pound by contrary Intelligence ſo that its hoped, their three dayes ore out of date, and their eyes quite put out, and they may wander with <hi>Rupert</hi> and <hi>Maurice</hi> to <hi>Ireland</hi> to cry <hi>Oh hone:</hi> for here's no more plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be obtained in <hi>England.</hi> Theſe his predictions in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Aſtrology I have repeated, becauſe they are excellent and notable expreſsions in the Art and manifeſtly viſible. They that would be further ſatisfyed repaire to the books themſelves. For what I have performed in the enſuing Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, I leave to the candid cenſure of the well diſpoſed, and doe hope as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> and my ſelfe have the ſame principles in Art, ſo our judgements in the generall, and my owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular notion upon the ſollid foundation of Art will have, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable ſucceſſe. I hartily wiſh all happineſſe to our preſent Parliament, and abundant of bleſsing to the City of <hi>London,</hi> wherein I now inhabit, pray to God preſerve both States in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Concord, that ſo the Affaires of the Publique may more vigorouſly be proſecuted, Religion eſtabliſhed, and Peace univerſally ſucceed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So wiſheth a true</hi> Engliſh <hi>man, an Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebellion: One that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the Peace of Church and State, and the utter extirpation of Popery. JOHN BOOKER</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="almanac">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113488:4"/>
            <head>A Bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> ALMANACK for the YEERE 1646.</head>
            <p>NOt many dayes after the <hi>Iriſh Cabinet,</hi> or his Majeſties <hi>Secret Papers</hi> for eſtabliſhing the Papall Clergy in <hi>Ireland</hi> came to publick view (which is worthy to be peruſed by all true hearted Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi>) There appeared an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Almanack, intituled thus, <hi>A new Almanack for the yeere of our Lord God</hi> 1646. <hi>being the ſecond after Leap yeere, and ſince the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World</hi> 5595. <hi>Calculated for the Longitude and Latitude of the City of</hi> Waterford <hi>and may ſerve generally for all</hi> Ireland; <hi>By an</hi> Manapian. Waterford, <hi>Printed for the Yeere</hi> MDCXLVI. Which Almanack I having had ſight of, and peruſing the ſame, I found many remarkable and memorable Chronologicall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, agreeing ſo exactly with the tranſaction of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and preſent affaires betweene his Majeſty and the bloody <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who are called his Majeſties <hi>Catholick Subjects:</hi> That I held it a great injury to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation if the ſame ſhould have been ſmothered, and not divulged; I meane ſo much thereof as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the inveterate hatred of that inhumane people againſt the Parliament, and the whole Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> The other part being either Popiſh Saints dayes, or vulgar Obſervations in moſt common Almanacks, I paſſed by as not materiall to the preſent taske in hand, and indeede the whole of it, and all of them I judge worthy no other then the fire.</p>
            <p>In the leafe next the Title page, Thus it is Printed. <hi>Our moſt Gracious King</hi> Charles <hi>began his Raigne over great</hi> Brittaine <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>the</hi> 27 <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1625. <hi>And hath Raigned</hi> 21 <hi>yeares compleate the</hi> 26 <hi>of March</hi> 1646. <hi>But the</hi> 27 <hi>day we write</hi> Anno Regni 22 <hi>Whom God proſper in all his Deſignes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Rebellious Subjects the</hi> ☞ ROVNDHEADS <hi>of</hi> ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>I truſt God will not heare, their prayer but turne it into <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Abomination, Pſal.</hi> 109.7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.9. Hath the King Deſignes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113488:5"/> his Subjects? Are his Subjects termed Rebells? Are they pointed out for deſtruction by a bloody hand, and called the <hi>Roundheads</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> O God blaſt all ſuch deſignes! And all yee true hearted <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, looke about you, unite your ſelves againſt the common Enemy, the blood-thirſty <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Papiſts, Jeſuites, and their confederates, <hi>&amp;c, Why doe the Heathen rage and the people imagine a vaine thing? The Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take Councell together, againſt the Lord and againſt his anointed, Saying, Let us breake their bands aſunder and caſt their coards from us; He that ſitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, The Lord ſhall have them in diviſion, he ſhall ſpeake to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure; He ſhall breake them with a rod of iron, and daſh them in peeces like a Potters v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll; Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth, ſerve the Lord with feare and rejoyce with trembling; Kiſſe the Sonne leaſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little, But bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Iriſh</hi> note which I obſerve, is as followeth; In the month of <hi>January</hi> over againſt the 10 day in (bloody) red letters, this <hi>Manapian,</hi> one borne in <hi>Menapia,</hi> a City or Towne in the County of <hi>Weisford</hi> or <hi>Wexford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Wexford</hi> it ſelfe, as <hi>Camden</hi> thinks in his Deſcription of <hi>Ireland, fol.</hi> 89. <hi>mihi,</hi> ſets it downe thus. <hi>The moſt pernitious Anarchicall Rebellion of the</hi> Roundheads <hi>of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>It may be remembred that <hi>January</hi> the firſt 1641, The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment petitioned the King for a Guard, foreſeeing a deſigne upon them; And the next day the Kings Anſwer was, He tendred their ſafety as his owne, and their life as the life of his children; But the fourth day he came in perſon to the Houſe of Commons at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with about foure hundred perſons, with Swords, Piſtolls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to demand the five Members, which unparallel'd attempt diſcovered the deſigne of the Enemy to make warre againſt the Parliament, which afterward followed; yea and the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King himſelfe came to the <hi>Guild Hall</hi> in <hi>London</hi> at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell, to what intent, appeared in few dayes: for this tenth day mentioned in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Almanacke, The King, with the Queen, Prince, Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> left <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and went to <hi>Hampton-Court;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113488:5"/> ever ſince which time to this very day (having forſaken his Parliament, and left his people out of his protection) hath beene the moſt horrible, bloody, unnaturall warre that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> nay, in all the world, it being never knowne that a King againſt his people, his Parliament, his Kingdomes, ſhould raiſe warre, till ſoone after that time in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Calendar men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And now let all the world judge whether this <hi>Manapian</hi> be not a moſt <hi>Malignant, lying, pernitious, Antichriſtian</hi> Iriſh <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> that ſo falſly ſlandereth the Parliament and Kingdome, by calling their juſt actions <hi>Anarchicall Rebellion,</hi> and the people thereof the <hi>Roundheads</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Over againg the 23 of <hi>October</hi> in the Almanack, This Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound in (bloody) red letters, writes, thus, <hi>The happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholicks eo die.</hi> This is that infamous, that fatlla day, the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641, when that unparallel'd <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Iriſh</hi> violently burſt forth to the maſſacring &amp; deſtruction of many thouſands of innocent Proteſtants in that Kingdome by a crew of Devills incarnate, who pleade Commiſſion for this inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Act, and call it <hi>The happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholicks:</hi> This 23 day of <hi>October</hi> 1641 I could wiſh were marked with <hi>Carbone nigre,</hi> or for ever were deleated out of the <hi>Calendar:</hi> But when I obſerved that very day twelve moneth, <hi>viz.</hi> the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1642. How juſt God was in puniſhing (though not the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation yet) the Abetters of them and their horrible Rebellion, in that memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Victory it pleaſed God to give the Parliaments Forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of their then Lord Generall, the Right noble Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> betweene <hi>Keynton</hi> and <hi>Edgehill</hi> againſt the Enemy; I am ſtruck with admiration, and with me it ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. How the <hi>Oxford Naworths,</hi> and this <hi>Iriſh Manapians</hi> Almanack agree, ſeemes to me ſomewhat ſtrange. The <hi>Oxonian</hi> calls it <hi>The Grand Rebellion,</hi> he meanes the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1642 when the Battell at <hi>Keynton</hi> was, But I meane that black day the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641, when the <hi>Iriſh</hi> unparrallel'd <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> burſt out, which this <hi>Manapian</hi> termes <hi>The happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholicks,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Almanack, and <hi>The happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholicks</hi> in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are both one; Though there was a Rebellion but in one, yet they were both united in the proſecution of a moſt bloody warre; what was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113488:6"/> by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in 1641 in that Kingdome againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants there, was in 1642, on the ſame day vehemently purſued by their Confederates againſt the Proteſtants here; There is a time drawing neere when the <hi>Oxfords</hi> Almanack <hi>Grand Rebellion,</hi> and, <hi>The happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholicks in Ireland</hi> will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and both of them called to a ſtrict account for the ſame.</p>
            <p>There are ſome admirable Aſtrologicall Obſervations which happened on theſe two dayes <hi>viz.</hi> the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641: And that 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1642: On that in 1641 (though not viſibly to be ſeene) was a great and terrible Eclipſe of the Sun in eleven degrees of <hi>Scorpio</hi> the oppoſite Signe to the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Moone then changing the 24 day cauſing ſuch a darkeneſſe in him in the morning, as if he were aſhamed to behold the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Iriſh</hi> maſſacring of the Proteſtants, which was diſcovered the 23 day by <hi>Owen Ockanellee</hi> then ſervant to Sir <hi>John Clotwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. Eclipſis Solis ſi fuerit in Scorpione fundamentorum ruinas, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eccleſiasticos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dia, ſimultates, &amp; turbas excitabunt, &amp; plebis &amp; turbae ignobilium interitus, diuturnaeque bellorum ſeditiones &amp;c deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Sic Jo. Anton. Giuffus in tractatu de Eclipſibus.</hi> That is, If the Sun ſhall be eclipſed in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> it threatens deſtruction of Ancient Foundations, and ſtirres up hatred and grudgings and debates amongſt Eccleſiaſticks. The death of the common, or ignoble people, and continuall ſeditions of warre. And <hi>Proclus</hi> ſayes if the Sun ſhall be eclipſed in the firſt ten degrees of <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, Tumultus bellicos movet, cades, odia, captivitates &amp; proditiones machinatur.</hi> That is, It ſtirres up warre-like tumults, ſlaughters, hatred, captivities and treacheryes it doth threaten; And if in the ſecond ten degrees of <hi>Scorpio</hi> (as this was) <hi>Regis cujuſpiam perniciem, averſum exercitus animum.</hi> Part of this prediction is already fullfilled, and if God prevent it not, the reſidue is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching very neere. It began to operate that very day, and hath continued in much virulency to this very time. But the next 23 of <hi>October viz.</hi> 1642: was moſt memorable when <hi>Mars</hi> who was Lord of the ſaid Eclipſe met in oppoſition to the Sun, was that Signall great Battell fought at <hi>Keynton:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kings Army and the Parliaments. Both which dayes and configurations <hi>Mars</hi> was extreamely afflicted by being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113488:6"/> to his houſes. In the firſt he was in <hi>Libra,</hi> and in the ſecond in <hi>Taurus:</hi> very fatall to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and that party their Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates. I gave a touch of that in <hi>October</hi> 1642 in my Almanacke, amongſt other thus much, <hi>Caedes quoque cruentae, &amp; lites atrae hinc inde percrebeſcent, Edgehill</hi> Battell can witneſſe this, The number that was ſlaine on both ſides there, are not yet knowne; This 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1642: the Sun was in ten degrees of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Taurus</hi> retrograde in the oppoſite Signe and neere the degree oppoſing: And I well remember what <hi>Origanus</hi> ſays Par: 3. <hi>de effectibus.</hi> Fol: 522: <hi>Pertinet ad fidem &amp; diligentiam Aſtrologorum, omnium quantum fieri poteſt Principum, Ducum, Comitum, Nobilium, Conſulum, praecipuorum quoque Theologorum, Epiſcoporum, Conſiliariorum, Medicorum, Genituras inquirere; Non enim magna ſolummodò laut eſt, priori conſulta experientia de ipſis in ſpecie aliquid dicere: Sed publica quoque fata ex eorum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute pendent: Quicquid enim delirant reges plectuntur Achivi:</hi> That is, It is for the credit of Aſtrologers as much as in them lyes to ſearch into the Nativities of Princes, Dukes, Earles, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Conſuls. (<hi>i. e.</hi> Mayors) or chiefe Officers of Cityes or Townes, Prime Divines, Biſhops, Councellours, Phyſicians, &amp;c. For there is not onely great prayſe (experience being had of them particularly) But the Publicke Affaires or Commonwealth depends on their wellfare: And moſt men frame themſelves to the minde of the King. I am not ignorant of this, and have had ſome experience of late of this Aphoriſme, And this I dare boldly ſay, that what ever he be from <hi>Caeſarto Codrus,</hi> if he have at the time of his Nativity the tenth degree, or within five de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, <hi>ante &amp; retro</hi> of <hi>Scorpio, Leo, Aquary,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Taurus,</hi> culminating, Horoſcopicall, The Sun, Moone, or part of Fortune in the ſame or neere it, He, ſhe, or they will ſuffer extreamely in one kinde or other, ſome in their Honours, Eſtates, Dignities, Some in their Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſome in all of them: I know ſome, and thoſe no meane ones; But, <hi>Cynthius Aureno vellit;</hi> Our King is either miſled, or willfull: For the firſt, <hi>Take away the wicked from before the King and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Prov.</hi> 25.5. But if he continue in this ſtrange unheard of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from the Parliament, whereby, not onely through the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of due and juſt governing of his people, both his and their ruin
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113488:7"/> muſt inevitably ſucceed, I muſt remember him of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> yea God changeth the Times and the Seaſons, <hi>He removeth Kings and ſetteth up Kings, Dan.</hi> 2.21. Who knowes but that the Hand-writing upon the Wall may be applicable to this preſent, miſerable, deplorable time we live in? for my part I tremble to thinke to what ſad condition many will be brought in ſhort time if God Almighty prevent not: But <hi>Quos vult perdere Jupiter hos dementat.</hi> And now though theſe two diſmall Aſpects in <hi>October</hi> be paſt, their Effects continue; And this yeare in <hi>April</hi> are many notable meetings of the Planets in the Signe <hi>Taurus</hi> (governing <hi>Ireland</hi>) As firſt of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> on the 12 day, <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> the 14 day, the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> the 17 day, the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> the 18 day, and <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> the 20 day, all of them in the firſt Face of <hi>Taurus,</hi> between the 6 and 10 degree of the ſaid ſigne; Lord, what preparations doe the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and their confederate Friends the papall Party here, there, and from forraigne parts make? what Conſultations, Meſſages, Embaſſyes, what Treacheries? what combinations, what Conſpiracies doe they frame againſt the poore Proteſtants of <hi>England, &amp;c?</hi> But the longeſt day muſt have an end; And on that day this yeere, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturne Lerma Lerma reſonabunt</hi> who meeting in conjunction in the midſt of <hi>Taurus,</hi> will ſound fearfull Alarmes in the midſt of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but of theſe more anon.</p>
            <p>I thought to have found in the next Moneth, in this <hi>Iriſh Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack,</hi> viz. <hi>November</hi> on the 5 day, ſome commemoration of that damnable powder Plot 1605, that Popiſh, helliſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy to deſtroy the <hi>Parliament;</hi> but they in <hi>Ireland</hi> would be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of that, as not long ſince our corrupt, ambitious Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Clergy endeavoured to have brought the ſame about here, but let us in <hi>England</hi> for ever remember Gods mercy, and be thankfull in our deliverance from the damnable Treaſon of the Papiſts, on our 5 day of <hi>November,</hi> 1605. Where there was both a Plot and powder: And let us not forget the fearfull judgement of God, in the downefall of <hi>Black-Fryers</hi> upon the Papiſts, (the 26 of our <hi>October</hi>) being the 5 of their <hi>November,</hi> 1623. where was no Plot, nor powder. <hi>O miranda Dei Judicis aequitas, fraudis fraud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſua prenditu Artifex, &amp; quis alios plagis irretire parabant h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſere impliciti pedes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113488:7"/>
               <l>The wicked people in the pit, are fallen themſelves that digged it,</l>
               <l>Yea their owne feet are faſt inſnar'd, in hidden nets themſelves prepar'd.</l>
               <l>And thereby hath the Lord been known, for having ſuch a judgement ſhown</l>
               <l>In that the wicked are ſurpriz'd, even in the ſnare themſelves devis'd.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They in <hi>Ireland</hi> begin their <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> as this <hi>Iriſh</hi> Almanack hath it, on the 3 day of <hi>November,</hi> on which day of <hi>November</hi> 1640. this happy <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (ſo much endeavoured to be diſſolved) began, but their Terme and our <hi>Parliament</hi> are heterogenean, Our <hi>Parliament</hi> ere long will alter their Terme, and as their Rebellion broke forth the 23 of <hi>October,</hi> ſo we now begin our Terme on the 23 of <hi>October,</hi> as if one ſhould ſay, all the Courts of Juſtice in <hi>England</hi> by a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence, were opened to give Judgement againſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> for their Rebellion againſt them the 23 of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well! This 23 of <hi>October</hi> will be remembred as a day of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by the Parliament and whole Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> for their great deliverance out of the hands of their cruell Enemy at <hi>Keyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Battell, when the bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>His Race and all his Generation,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſuffer utter extirpation,</l>
                  <l>And in the Age that next doth follow</l>
                  <l>Oblivion ſhall his black name ſwallow.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It may very well be ſaid of <hi>Ireland, Bona Terra, malu Gens.</hi> But when that wicked Generation of men have drunke their fill of the bloud of the Saints: then ſhall they as deepely drinke of the Cup of Gods wrath. <hi>Quod differtur, non aufertur.</hi> The time haſteneth, and is neerer then they are aware of.</p>
            <p>I have briefely run over theſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Notes which this <hi>Manapian</hi> in behalfe of that Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to the ſame end as <hi>Naworth</hi> and <hi>Wharton</hi> the <hi>Oxfordians</hi> publiſh theirs in malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament and the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> have done; Thereby diſcovering themſelves to be a moſt Viperous Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: There are ſome other obſervations I might have made on the Popiſh Saints dayes, which in this Almanack are very thin: I hope in the next that is written, there will be none at all. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113488:8"/> had this <hi>Iriſh Manapian</hi> beene as learned in Aſtrology as <hi>Wharton</hi> is, and predicted as much as he did upon the Kings (unfortunate) march the ſeventh of <hi>May</hi> the laſt yeare, I ſhould have hoped the like ſucceſſe as ever ſince hath befallen that Party. My Friend Maſter <hi>Lilly</hi> in his Poſtſcript to his <hi>Starry-Meſſenger</hi> lately Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hath ſufficiently refuted that <hi>Bloxford Aſtrolo-gazeſtar.</hi> We neede not feare either of them, one more then the other. <hi>There is a lying Spirit in the mouth of all of them.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.21. Their Religion, their Learning, is one and the ſame; their Knowledge in Aſtrology very neere of kin. There is not a <hi>Lunation,</hi> that is, A <hi>New Moone, Full Moone,</hi> or her other Quarters, mentioned throughout this Popiſh Calendar, that is truely ſet downe; Some of them twelve houres, ſome a day, ſome two dayes, and many three dayes erring from the truth. I am ſure of it never a one of them fitted to the <hi>Meridian</hi> of any part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for which it was intended, nor for <hi>England,</hi> againſt whom it was penned, printed and publiſhed; So that if the <hi>Oxford</hi> Writers take their Obſervations, and ground their Judgements from the Lunations in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Almanack, we ſhall not neede to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed at their pradictions, And the fayre weather in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Almanack will prove foule to them, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> come to correct the Printing Preſſe at <hi>Waterford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am now come to the end of the Calendar, and in the next page I finde ſet downe, The riſing and ſetting of the Sun for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt and fifteenth day of every moneth in the yeare. Why? <hi>God maketh his Sun to riſe on the evill, and on the good and ſendeth raine on the just, and on the unjuſt. Math.</hi> 5.45. There is likewiſe the length of the day ſet downe; If they pleaſe to remember the Battell at <hi>Naſeby</hi> the laſt yeare, they will have ſmall cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the 12 of <hi>June</hi> this yeare, (or not many dayes after.) Truely the longeſt day will be for ever fatall to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, if my Aſtrologie faile not, and they know it ſeldome does.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113488:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>After this Table followes A Compendious Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of things Memorable.</head>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>From the Creation to <hi>Noahs Flood, Gen.</hi> 5.7.11. -1060 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From the <hi>Flood</hi> to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 11.32 12.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.4. -356 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From <hi>Abrahams</hi> birth to <hi>Terah's</hi> death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.32.12.4.- 80 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From <hi>Terah's</hi> death to <hi>Iſraels</hi> delivery, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.40, 41. -434 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From that time till <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.1.- 484 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From the building of <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple to Chriſt.- 1032 Yeares.</item>
                     <item>From Chriſts birth till this yeares end. -1646 Yeares.</item>
                  </list> The full Sum from the Creation to this yeares end is 5092 Yeares.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This <hi>Iriſh</hi> Chronologer hath computed by his falſe Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick the aboveſaid numbers of yeares to be 5595, as he ſets down both in the Frontiſpice of his Almanacke, and in this place, but both are equally erroneous. It is true, <hi>Non levis inter viros Doctos rerum hiſtoricarum annotationibus exiſtit controverſia:</hi> That is, There is no ſmall controverſie amongſt learned men in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations of Hiſtoricall matters; Truely, there is great diverſity amongſt them in many memorable Chronologicall Computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; But never any that ever I read of computed leſſe then 1656 yeares from the Creation to the Flood; So that this <hi>Iriſh</hi> account is ſhort of the truth (in this very particular) no leſſe then 596 yeares; now if we adde theſe 596 yeares to 5092 they will make
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113488:9"/> in all 5688 which is too many by 93 yeares, ſo that there is no truth at all in this compendious Chronology: Methinks when I ſee 88. I call to minde that <hi>Annus ominoſus &amp; fatalis,</hi> The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, <hi>Cum formidabilis illa</hi> Claſſis Hiſpanica <hi>profligatur ab An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glis Duce</hi> Franciſco Drake; That terrible Armado, The lively portraiture whereof is repreſented in thoſe curious Works in the Lords Houſe now in Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> But as that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado</hi> then was <hi>Ventorum Ludibrium</hi> and was by Gods providence totally defeated by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> So the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion will have like ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Then follows the remainder of this Compendious Chronology with
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Since the deſtruction of</hi> Troy 2830 yeares.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This may be ſomething neere truth, for all Writers agree that it was before Chriſt 1183 yeares; now if we adde 1646 being the yeares ſince Chriſt Birth, to 1183 the yeares before his Birth, they will make 2829 ſince the deſtruction of <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then followes, ſince <hi>Bartholenus</hi> entred this Iſland of <hi>Ireland</hi> 4235 yeares, who this <hi>Bartholenus</hi> I cannot learne, but it ſeemes he came in the yeare of the world 1360, which was 296 yeares before the Flood, which I prove thus. If you ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract 4235 yeares from 5595 there will remaine 1360, and if you ſubſtract this 1360 from 1656, (the yeare of the World when the Flood was) there will remaine 296. I beleeve he was one of the Off-ſpring of <hi>Cain,</hi> though <hi>Camden</hi> relates (in his deſcription of <hi>Ireland, fol.</hi> 64.) that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſay that he was a <hi>Scythian,</hi> (and then he came of <hi>Magog</hi>) who deſcended from <hi>Japeth,</hi> and that he fought right doughty Battells with Gyants: In theſe times men lived many hundreds of yeares, but when the Flood came all the People of the Earth were drowned, ſave eight Perſons, which were <hi>Noah</hi> and his wife with his three ſonnes, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, Ham</hi> and <hi>Japeth,</hi> and their Wives: Now amongſt all theſe there was never a <hi>Bartholènus,</hi> and if there had been any ſuch a one, doubtleſſe he had periſhed amongſt the reſt in the Flood; If he came not from <hi>Cain</hi> before the Flood,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113488:9"/> ſurely he deſcended from <hi>Ham</hi> who was the Father of <hi>Canaan</hi> after the Flood; from theſe three ſonnes of <hi>Noah,</hi> all the Earth was overſpread; now <hi>Noah</hi> curſed <hi>Canaan</hi> and ſaid, <hi>a Servant of Servants ſhall he be unto his brethren;</hi> To what purpoſe this <hi>Bartholenus</hi> is mentioned to have entred <hi>Ireland,</hi> or who he was, it much matters not, neither if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> came from him, or from whom elſe; this I am ſure of they are now a People farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the moſt barbarous <hi>Caniballs,</hi> and inhumane bloudy men that ever I read of in any Hiſtory: Here may be moved a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, why <hi>Canaan</hi> being curſed, he ſhould poſſeſſe the moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile place and part of the World, a Land flowing with milke and Honey; ſo may I ſay of <hi>Ireland,</hi> why ſuch a good Country ſhould be beſtowed on ſo wicked a People, I much wonder at it; it rather ſhewes a bleſſing then a curſe, and that they ſhould rather be Lords then ſervants; but as one ſayes, <hi>Cum Iſraelitae deletis omnibus iſtis gentibus (viz. Sidoniis, Tyriis, Hethaeis, Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeis, Amorhaeis, Gergeſaeis, Hevaeis, Cannanaeis, &amp;c. terram Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanaeam ingrederentur: tunc ſauè manifeſtata eſt veritas maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Nohae, dederuntque paenas impietatis ſuae, ejecti &amp; exciſi per populum Dei, quem tandem triumphare oportet;</hi> It is juſt the State and Condition of <hi>Ireland</hi> as then of <hi>Canaan;</hi> And they muſt looke for the like meaſure of puniſhment by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation, as <hi>Canaan</hi> did by the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then follows, ſince the building of the City of <hi>Waterford</hi> by <hi>Sitaracus</hi> 1491 yeares. This <hi>Sitaracus</hi> it ſeemes was about the yeare of Chriſt 155. About which time, <hi>Valentinian</hi> an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian,</hi> that damnable Heretique, ſpread his wicked Tenents, and about this time lived <hi>Higinus</hi> the firſt that ſtiled himſelfe <hi>Pope of Rome;</hi> This City by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> is called <hi>Porth-Largy,</hi> as <hi>Camden</hi> ſayes in his deſcription of <hi>Ireland</hi> fol. 79. And was built by certain <hi>Pyrates</hi> of <hi>Norway</hi> But I make a great queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Antiquity of it, neither is it to purpoſe: Onely it is obſervable that <hi>Pyrates</hi> were the founders of <hi>Waterford.</hi> I am ſure of it Printing was not then uſed, but it ſeemes now they have got a Printing Preſſe there; Whether it and the materials came from <hi>Rome, Doway, Rhim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or any ſuch other <hi>Popiſh</hi> place I know not; But they there, and at <hi>Oxford</hi> of late and now,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113488:10"/> print baſe and railing Pamphlets, and lying <hi>Almanacks,</hi> and in them moſt groſſely abuſe the Parliament and Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> who no doubt ere long will ſuppreſſe their Preſſes.</p>
            <p>Now followes ſince the building of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> 2397 yeares, about the yeare of the world 3198. It is a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute amongſt <hi>Chronologers</hi> and <hi>Hiſtoriographers</hi> when <hi>Rome</hi> was built; Some of them as <hi>Beroſus</hi> and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſner</hi> ſay. The firſt foundation was layde in the yeare of the World, 2341 by <hi>Roma</hi> daughter to <hi>Atlas,</hi> or <hi>Kitim</hi> King of <hi>Italy,</hi> about thirty yeers before the Birth of <hi>Moſes:</hi> Some, yea the moſt thinke, that it was built by <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus,</hi> as <hi>Livy, Dion,</hi> and others relate; The Story is thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Procas</hi> King of <hi>Latium,</hi> or the <hi>Latines,</hi> having left his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (after he had raigned three and twenty yeares) to his two Sonnes <hi>Amulius</hi> and <hi>Numitor</hi> to rule by yearely turnes: <hi>Amulius</hi> having gotten poſſeſſion, keepes the Kingdome by ſtrong hold, and cauſeth <hi>Numitor</hi> his Brother to live privately; And becauſe <hi>Amulius</hi> would not live in feare of <hi>Numitors</hi> iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, he enticed <hi>Lauſus</hi> or <hi>Egeſtus, Numitors</hi> Sonne to goe hunt with him, and then and there ſlew him; And cauſed his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Rhea,</hi> or <hi>Ilia,</hi> to become a Veſtall Virgin to keepe her from marriage, or children; But he was deceived; For in the fourth yeare of his raigne, which was (as ſome ſuppoſe) in the yeare of the World, 3158. She was great with childe (by an unknowne man) but many thinke (by <hi>Amulius</hi> himſelfe in diſguiſe) becauſe he knew ſhe ſhould dye, if the breach of her Vow appeared by a great belly) and was delivered of <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus</hi> at a Birth; For which ſhe was buried quick, or beaten to death with Rods. But <hi>Dion</hi> ſaith, ſhe was ſaved at the requeſt of <hi>Amulius</hi> his daughter, but <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus</hi> were delivered to ſome to be caſt into <hi>Tiber</hi> in a cradle, which could not be effected, becauſe the River was overflowne; So they were left upon a Banke. <hi>Fauſtulus</hi> the chiefe Shepheard to <hi>Amulius,</hi> being at Court, having heard their doome, Followed, Found, and carried them to his wife <hi>Acca Laurentia,</hi> called by the people for her luſt: and the <hi>Stewes</hi> of her <hi>Lupanaria, Lupa,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113488:10"/> Hence aroſe this Fiction, That they were nurſed by a <hi>Shee-Woolſe.</hi> She delivered them to a woman that had loſt a childe a little before of her owne. At the age of eighten yeares, theſe Brothers fell out with <hi>Numitors</hi> Shepheard about feeding of their Flocks; But when <hi>Romulus</hi> was abſent, <hi>Remus</hi> was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before <hi>Amulius,</hi> who upon their Complaint delivered him to <hi>Numitor</hi> to put him to death; but <hi>Fauſtulus</hi> perceiving the danger, revealed their birth to <hi>Romulus</hi> (who reputed <hi>Fauſtulus</hi> till that time to be his Father) and to <hi>Numitor,</hi> upon a conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they aſſaulted <hi>Amulius,</hi> ſlew him, and reſtored <hi>Numitor</hi> to the Kingdome, who gave leave to them, to build Cityes; <hi>Romulus</hi> choſe the Mount <hi>Palatine,</hi> and built <hi>Rome,</hi> and this was <hi>Anno Mundi.</hi> 3198 as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Computator reckons, I will not much trouble my ſelfe concerning the truth of this Story: Onely it is obſervable that <hi>Rome</hi> was built, founded by Bloud, Murther, Luſt, Treachery, &amp;c. And I know not why I may not ſuppoſe the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation to come from that <hi>Lupa;</hi> For they are all of them of the ſame Religion, with thoſe, nay, of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Whore of Babylon;</hi> That Countrey of <hi>Ireland</hi> hath had many Wolves in it, but never more then now. And <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in his deſcription of <hi>Ireland</hi> Fol. 83. ſayes, ſome of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and ſuch as would be thought worthy of Credit, doe affirme that certaine men (in the County of <hi>Tipperary</hi>) are yearely turned into Wolves; Whether it be a meere fable, or no, I matter it not; Unleſſe that malignant humour of unkind Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy predominate in them, and ſo cauſe that diſeaſe which Phyſicians call <hi>Lycanthropia,</hi> and ſo they imagine themſelves to be transformed into Wolves: However, that malignant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour hath reigned amongſt them above this foure yeares. That now the people are become more ſalvage and bloudy then Wolves, or any other creature whatſoever; But this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Phyſician that can under God cure all diſtempers of Church and State, will cure <hi>Ireland</hi> of its <hi>Lycanthropia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> was many yeares ago rid of Wolves, by deſtroying them. And I have read that King <hi>Edgar</hi> impoſed a taske upon <hi>Ludwall,</hi> a Prince in <hi>Wales,</hi> to preſent yeerely to him three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Wolves or their skins for a Tribute, which he did for three
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113488:11"/> yeares together; But the fourth yeere he gave over, proteſting he could find no more. What King <hi>Edgar</hi> did I know not, but thankes be to God there are no Wolves in <hi>England</hi> (but of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> breed) Though there hath beene an endeavour to bring over, hath beene, and now are, and are daily expected ſome Wolviſh <hi>Iriſh</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> This I am ſure of, This Parliament hath paſſed an Ordinance of the 24 of <hi>October</hi> 1644 <hi>That no Quarter ſhall be given to any</hi> Iriſh <hi>man nor to any Papiſts whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever borne in</hi> Ireland <hi>which ſhall be taken in hoſtility against the Parliament, either upon the Sea, or within this Kingdome or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of</hi> Wales, <hi>But that they ſhall be excepted out of all Capitulations, Agreements, or Compoſitions with the Enemy, And every ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be put to death; Nay, any Officer by Sea or Land, that ſhall be remiſſe, or negligent in the obſerving the Tenor of this Ordinance, ſhall be reputed a Favourer of that Bloody Rebellion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and ſhall be liable to ſuch condigne puniſhment as the Juſtice of both Houſes of Parliament ſhall inflict upon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> I truſt this Ordinance will be throughly, and duly proſecuted, and then I hope both Kingdomes will ſhortly be cleared of the Wolves of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or the Wolviſh <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the building of <hi>Rome</hi> comes, ſince the Captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> by <hi>Cyrus</hi> 2284 yeares; This ſhould ſeeme to be in the yeere of the world 3311, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Computator reckons. But herein ſeverall Chronologers have their diverſitie of Opinions: This cannot poſſibly be true; for <hi>Cyrus</hi> began to rule over <hi>Perſia</hi> in the firſt of the 55 <hi>Olimpiade,</hi> which was <hi>Anno Mundi,</hi> 3390. So that here is 89 yeeres difference of this Computation; And in the yeere of the World 4409 <hi>Cyrus</hi> invaded <hi>Babylon,</hi> and conquered it, &amp;c. And in <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 4420. being the end of the 70 yeeres Captivity, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> and others thinke, he was in a ſecond battell with 200000 men defeated by <hi>Tomiris</hi> Queene of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> where himſelfe loſt his life: <hi>Tomiris</hi> cut off his head and threw it into a veſſell of blood. And now let the <hi>Iriſh</hi> remember her ſaying to dead King <hi>Cyrus, After blood thou didſt thirſt, and with blood thou ſhalt be ſatisfied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next enſues ſince the deſolation of the Temple of <hi>Salomon:</hi> 2251 yeares. This ſhould be in <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3344. In which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113488:11"/> yeare there was no ſuch thing done; It is true, the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah, Anno Mundi</hi> 3340, foretold of the deſtruction of the City <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and Temple, which came to paſſe twenty yeares after: For <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3360, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> tooke it, and deſtroyed it as <hi>Helvicus &amp;c</hi> reckons.</p>
            <p>Then comes, ſince <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> began his Empire 1686 yeers, And this after the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Accompt was <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3909. But here are ſeven years errour. For all Authors begin it <hi>Anno Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> 3902. And then the fourth Monarchy began in <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> who ruled Emperour but five yeares; After him came <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Caeſar, Anno Mundi</hi> 3906, and reigned 56 yeares, and in the 41 yeare of his reigne, which was <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3947, Our Saviour Chriſt was borne: Or as the received opinion is, <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3949. Now if we adde this 3949 to 1646, They will make 5595: The yeares ſince the Creation, as our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology reckons.</p>
            <p>After this followes, ſince <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> utterly deſtroyed by <hi>Veſpatian</hi> 1563 yeares: This ſhould have beene <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 83. But then there was no ſuch matter, for it was in <hi>Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 70: So that there is an errour of thirteene yeares defective, then there will be ſince <hi>Veſpatians</hi> deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 1576 yeares, as moſt Authors agree.</p>
            <p>After this followes, ſince <hi>Ireland</hi> firſt received the Catholicke faith by the preaching of the glorious Saint <hi>Patrick</hi> 1221 yeares, And this was <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 425. About this time, this <hi>Patrick</hi> lived: <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> the firſt being Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>Neſtorian</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie was much ſpread abroad; Many ſtrange things have beene reported of this <hi>Patrick.</hi> In memory of whom the 17 of <hi>March</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> celebrate as a Feſtivall. (But I ſhall take a courſe to croſſe him out of the Calendar) <hi>Hiberniae fuit Epiſcopus primus, &amp; imago illius exprimitur Serpentibus ad ejus pedes abjectis, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam Divina illius virtute hoc mirabiliter fieri traditur, ut nulla venenata beſtia ibi vivat. Petrus Galaſinius ex Beda, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſtor. Angl.</hi> That is, He was the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Image is portrayed with Serpents caſt under his feete: for that by his divine vertue, it wonderfully came to paſſe that no venemous Beaſts can live there. This is a miracle indeed, if it be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113488:12"/> true; Surely <hi>Panrick</hi> extracted all the Venome of Serpents, Toades, and ſuch like odious creatures then in <hi>Ireland;</hi> And by his preaching infuſed the ſame into the people. There were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Patrick</hi> came ſuch like creatures there: and there be now in <hi>Ireland</hi> more Venemous and Serpentine people then the very creatures themſelves can be in any other Countrey in the world, which this late Horrid Rebellion doth ſufficiently evince; But I hope there will be a Reformation there, as well as here, more glorious preaching then that of <hi>Patrick,</hi> or all Popiſh Biſhops, Prieſts Jeſuites &amp;c. And the Faith (Catholicke indeed) not in a Popiſh ſence; Though I conceive this <hi>Manapian,</hi> ſhould have ſaid ſince <hi>Ireland</hi> firſt received the Popiſh Catholicke faith, &amp;c. This had beene to purpoſe, and then I ſhould not have excepted againſt it.</p>
            <p>The next Chronologicall Obſervation is, Since <hi>England</hi> firſt received the <hi>Catholicke Faith</hi> 1463 yeeres. If he had ſaid ſince <hi>England</hi> firſt received the <hi>Chriſtian Catholicke Faith, &amp;c.</hi> it had beene ſomewhat neere truth; For King <hi>Lucius</hi> beginning his rule over the <hi>Brittaines,</hi> hearing of divers miracles wrought by the Chriſtians, and amongſt the reſt, of the plenty of Water in time of diſtreſſe and want thereof; as of the great Victory obtained <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 173 for the Emperour <hi>Marcus</hi> over the <hi>Marco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manni, &amp; Quadi</hi> by the prayers of the Chriſtian <hi>Legion,</hi> which he called <hi>Fulminatrix,</hi> ſent to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> then Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> to ſend him ſome learned men into <hi>Brittaine,</hi> to inſtruct the people in the Faith; whereupon he ſent <hi>Damianus</hi> and <hi>Fugatius,</hi> who Baptized King <hi>Lucius</hi> and his people; He was the firſt Chriſtian King of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and lived neere the time of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Primitive purity, when Popiſh Catholicke Religion was not heard of: If any of the Popes were ought, this Pope <hi>Eluthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> was none of the worſt, He prohibited the ſuperſtitious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall of eating any thing which was mans meate, <hi>Et primus erat Epiſcoporum Romanorum qui non periit morte violenta.</hi> King <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> built <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill London</hi> about 430 yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, which was built by King <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> who began his raigne <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 596.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113488:12"/>
            <p>After follows, ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond arrived at this City of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and the firſt Major of it, 474. yeers. This is neer an hiſtoricall truth; for <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1170. or thereabout; at what time that ambitious, turbulent, fiery ſpirited Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Thomas Becket</hi> was ſlain: This King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond had wars with <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the next yeer he ſubdued it; and I ſuppoſe King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond at his comming to <hi>Waterford,</hi> made it a Major Town (and indeed as moſt men that have been there report it to be the ſecond City in all <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have granted great priviledges to the ſame:) Who this Major was, our Iriſh Chronologer doth not name; I beleeve he was an Engliſh, not an Iriſh man, for I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive otherwiſe, but they were then rebellious as now; ſo that there is greater neceſſity of correcting their preſent rebellion, by a new ſupply of valiant Engliſh men, who if they land at <hi>Waterford,</hi> the preſent Major may chance to be diſplaced, and the Citizens loſe their liberty.</p>
            <p>The next is ſince the uſe of Guns, invented in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the firſt making of Powder by a Fryar, <hi>Bartholdus Swartz,</hi> 263. yeer. This doth not much differ from the ſuppoſed time of their known uſe in Chriſtendom, although I have read that in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, who flouriſhed about the yeer of Chriſt 800. <hi>Camoſcus Friſiae Rex Slopeti ictu Hollandiae Comitem, cum duobus filijs tranſuerberavit:</hi> and <hi>Roger Bacan</hi> our famous Hiſtorian who flouriſhed about the yeer or Chriſt 1280. makes mention of Gun-powder; and I beleeve what <hi>Petrus Maffeus</hi> writes, that Guns were of great antiquity, and known in <hi>China</hi> many Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies of yeers before they were uſed in Chriſtendome: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let us ſuppoſe, that <hi>Bartholdus Niger vulgo Swartz Monachus Franciſcanus &amp; Alchymista uſum Bombardae vulgavit pro ut nunc eſt anno Christi</hi> 1380. as <hi>Alsteed</hi> ſayes in his Chronologie, <hi>Orig. var. pag. mihi.</hi> 256. I think the Adage, <hi>Turdus ſibi malum cacat,</hi> or as we in <hi>England</hi> have it, he hath made a rod for his own breech, will be exactly verefied this yeer: Look to it all ye Iriſh Popiſh Fryars, Monks, Jeſuits &amp;c. and the reſt of that rabble of Locuſts, there are new Guns, new Ordnances inventing, preparing, that will purge and cleer the three Kingdoms of all of you.</p>
            <p>Now this Iriſh Chronologer, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> like ſpets forth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113488:13"/> and rores out, which ſince Lutheraniſm, Calviniſme, and ſuch like hereſies began in <hi>Germany</hi> 128. yeers; he that would be throughly ſatisfied touching this worthy Doctor <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> this <hi>Malleus Paparum &amp; Papistarum,</hi> may be pleaſed to peruſe the ſecond Tome of Acts and Monuments, or the Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, written by that reverend and learned man, Maſter <hi>John Fox,</hi> p. 60, 61. <hi>&amp; deinde,</hi> of the laſt Impreſſion 1641. he ſhall have his life and doctrine at large deſcribed; he flouriſhed in the yeer of Chriſt 1515. &amp;c. This is he of whom <hi>John Hus</hi> at the time of his Martyrdom propheſied, 1415. <hi>Centum Revolutis annis Deo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondebitis;</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> 1416. at his Martyrdom, who ſaid, <hi>Poſt Centum annos omnes vos Cito;</hi> now 100. yeers after <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Luther</hi> began firſt to write againſt the Pope, which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly verified; Reformation began in his time, he oppoſed the Popes ſupremacy, writ againſt his pardons, Decrees, Buls, and ſo ſtoutly defended himſelf againſt them, that he was excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by the Pope, and men hired to kill him; nay, the Devil, the Pope, the Emperour, and almoſt all the Chriſtian world were againſt him, and by open force and ſecret fraud ſought his deſtruction; yet God miraculouſly preſerved him for about thirty yeers ſpace, in deſpight of them all, and at laſt he dyed in hia bed in peace at <hi>Iſlebia</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> the 18. of Febr. 1546. from whence his body was removed to <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and there was buried the 22. of February 1546. it being juſt 100. yeers ſince, this Febr. 1646. at what time I write this: and now I may adde a third Propheſie or prediction, to cite all Iriſh Prieſts, and popiſh Fryars, &amp;c. <hi>Quod poſt centum annos Luthero re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondebitis;</hi> this Chronologer moſt falſly accuſing him of hereſie whoſe ſound doctrine hath ſo confuted the errours of thoſe ignorant times, that to this day the Papiſts could never anſwer him, but moſt maliciouſly traduce him: As for Maſter <hi>Calvin,</hi> he was a moſt reverend, orthodox man, and flouriſhed about the yeer of Chriſt. 1535. cotemporary with <hi>Bibliander, Marlorat, Viret, Muſculus, &amp;c.</hi> all learned, and men very excellent; it is moſt true, that from the yeer of Chriſt 800. to the yeer 1520. <hi>Paucae novae Haereſes ſunt Ortae, multa autem fuerant Sciſmata; ubi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellunt Sciſmata Pontificum Romanerum;</hi> that is, A few new hereſies ſprung up, and many were the Schiſms, but thoſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113488:13"/> Popes, Biſhops, exceeded them all, <hi>Alsted Chron. hereſium, pag.</hi> 390. And a little after the ſame <hi>Alsted</hi> ſaith, <hi>Verum tamen enim vero, non fuerint heretici illi Doctores, ſed Reformatores hereticae pravitatis in Regno Antichristi Romani;</hi> theſe Doctors were not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, but Reformers of the hereticall pravity, or corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Kingdome of the Pope, the Roman Antichriſt; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if you will look a little further in <hi>Alsted,</hi> he will tell you, that <hi>ab hoc anno, viz.</hi> 1520. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad nostram Aetatem pestilentes hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes ab inferis fuerunt revocatae, nam Principio Anabaptistae furere caepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp;c.</hi> Anabaptiſts, Antinomians, Socinians, Ubiquitarians, Arminians, &amp;c. were very buſie, and theſe were the Hereticks here meant, though for my part I ſuppoſe the greateſt Hereticks are Papiſts, Jeſuits, &amp;c. and of all in the world thoſe in <hi>Ireland</hi> the moſt damnable.</p>
            <p>Next followes, ſince the vertuous and holy Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> was beheaded in <hi>England,</hi> 46. yeers. Here is a manifeſt errour, for if ſo, then ſhe ſhould have been beheaded <hi>Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 1600. but that was not ſo, for ſhe was beheaded at <hi>Fothring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hay</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> the 18. of February 1587. which was 13. yeers before this Computiſt reckons; her body was buried at <hi>Peterborow,</hi> and 25. yeers after, <hi>viz.</hi> 1612. her body was removed to <hi>Westmninster;</hi> ſhe was born the 5. of December 1542. on which 5. of December 1560. <hi>Francis</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>France,</hi> who was her firſt husband dyed, being married to her 1558. the 13. of October; if you pleaſe to read <hi>Buchannan,</hi> that learned Scotchmans books, though they were prohobited 1584. ſome are extant, they will tell you more: I have read in <hi>Alsted,</hi> in his <hi>Chronologia Regni Scotiae Maria haec Anno</hi> 1558. <hi>nupſerat Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Regi Galliae; quo defuncto, redijt in Scotiam, ubi nupſit Henrico Arli, ſive Stuarto; quem interfici curavit; unde in Inſulam eſt deportata poſt elapſa in Angliam, Anno</hi> 1568. <hi>poſtquam</hi> 18. <hi>Annos captiva fuiſſet detenta, ibi eſt decollata;</hi> and in <hi>Saturni Ephemeride,</hi> Dedicated to King <hi>Charles</hi> pag. 382, <hi>Sub Titulo Scotland,</hi> it is there ſaid, that in the yeer 1564. ſhe fell in love with the Lord <hi>Darnley,</hi> ſon to the Earl of <hi>Lenox,</hi> got a Diſpenſation from the Pope for conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and created him Earl of <hi>Roſſe;</hi> the next yeer after, he is made Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> marrieth the Queen, and is proclaimed King; and that yeer that Duke of <hi>Chatteralt</hi> with divers Lords
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113488:14"/> being put to the Horn, fled into <hi>England,</hi> but returning are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled: The yeer 1566. Earl <hi>Morton</hi> and others fled into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and having murthered <hi>David Riſius</hi> the Queens Minion in her Chamber, <hi>Thaunus</hi> in his Hiſtory, <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 307. ſayes, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo vili conditione Citharaedi filius nomine</hi> David Rizius, <hi>Angustae Taurinaurum natus;</hi> and a little after, he ſaith, <hi>Faeminam per ſe praecipitem postremo impulit</hi> Rizius, <hi>qui plus apud eam, quam aut aequum aut ipſi decorum eſſet poterat;</hi> Earl <hi>Morton</hi> returneth into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and is pardoned; that yeer King <hi>James</hi> was born, and the next yeer, <hi>viz.</hi> 1567. the King her husband was murthered by Earl <hi>Bothwell;</hi> which Earl marrieih the Queen, ſhe goeth againſt the Diſcontented Lords, and is taken, <hi>Bothwell</hi> flies into <hi>Denmark,</hi> and there dyes in priſon, the Queen reſigneth, makes an eſcape, raiſeth forces, flies towards <hi>France,</hi> and is caſt on the Engliſh ſhore; much more may be read of her in the Scottiſh Hiſtory, to which I refer you: I ſhall uſe the words of <hi>Cambden</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Fothringhay</hi> Caſtle, fol. 511. As for that diſaſter which even here befell unto another moſt mighty Prince, <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of Scots, I had leiſer it ſhould be enwrapped up in ſilence, then once ſpoken of; let it be forgotten quite, if poſſible, if not, yet be it hidden, as it may, in ſilence.</p>
            <p>The next Chronologicall obſervation is, ſince the birth of our gracious King <hi>Charles,</hi> the 19. of Novemb. 46. yeers. This I beleeve is true, for I have often heard it reported, that he was born at <hi>Dunfermling</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the 19. of Novemb. 1600.</p>
            <p>Then ſucceeds ſince King <hi>Charles</hi> his return from <hi>Spain,</hi> Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the 5. 23. yeers, this I remember was in <hi>Anno</hi> 1623. and it rained all, or moſt part of that day at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Dic rogo cur toties Deſcendit ab Aethere nimbus</l>
               <l>Grandoque de Coelis ſic ſine fine Cadit?</l>
               <l>Mortales quoniam nolunt ſua crimina flere,</l>
               <l>Coelum pro nobis ſolvitur in Lachrymas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Then follows, ſince the Birth of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> May the 23. 15. yeers: This is erronious, for our Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was born the 29. of May 1630. which is 16. yeers ſince, at the revolution of this yeer 1646. and I very well remember the laſt of May be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113488:14"/> but two days after his birth, there was a great Eclipſe of the Sun in <hi>Gemini,</hi> the 19. degree, which was viſibly beheld here, and moſt part of Chriſtendom; all Authors agree, that eclipſes are very ominous, and we have had ſad experience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of of late yeers.</p>
            <p>Now comes again that <hi>memento</hi> with a witneſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> ſince the happy union of the Catholikes, for defence of his Majeſty, his royall Iſſue, &amp;c. which day is to be kept holy, for a day of Thankſgiving, being October 23. 1641. five yeers: I have ſaid enough already of this infamous 23. of October, and I hope it will be remembred, to the perpetuall ignominy of the bloody Rebels of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after that, are renumerated ſeverall victories ſince that Rebellion burſt forth, obtained by the Iriſh Confederates for his Majeſty againſt the Round-heads: I will not trouble my ſelf or the Reader to mention them, for I am confident they will ſing <hi>O hone</hi> very ſhortly. And the Iriſh,
<q>
                  <l>Their dayes a number ſmall ſhall make,</l>
                  <l>Another ſhall their Country take;</l>
                  <l>Their Children Vagabonds ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>Walk up and down moſt wretchedly;</l>
                  <l>God ſhall them put to endleſſe ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And quite cut off their hatefull name.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſhould tell this Iriſh Chronologer of the ſeverall wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Victories it hath pleaſed God to give the Parliaments For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſeverall parts of the three Kingdoms againſt a potent, powerfull, malicious, tyrannous and numerous Army, ſince the beginning of this Parliament, or ſince the moſt horrible Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of <hi>Ireland</hi> was kindled: I ſhould exceed and ſwel into a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, I will only deſire all the three Kingdoms to (nay all the world may) take notice of Gods, great and wonderfull mercy he hath ſhewn to the Parliaments Forces, in obtaining ſeverall Victories againſt, and ſtrong holds taken from the enemy ſince <hi>June</hi> 1645. to this preſent <hi>February,</hi> which may be read in a ſmall Tractate, entituled, <hi>Englands Remembrancer,</hi> abſtracted in a ſhort Catalogue lately printed; the number there computed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113488:15"/> ſeventy, all within ths ſpace of ſeven moneths; and ſince the publiſhing thereof, many more great victories; but amongſt the reſt, I will only mention the ſurrender of <hi>Chester</hi> (the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door for <hi>Ireland</hi>) to that faithfull man to his Country, Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Brereton;</hi> and now if I ſhould tell the Iriſh, they are never like to hear or ſay <hi>Maſſe</hi> there, or ever ſee their Unhallowed Candle again lighted, which was extinguiſhed the ſecond of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> laſt; they may chance to ſtorm, fret and fume at me, and and curſe with Bell, Book and Candle; all which will doe me or any man elſe as much hurt juſt as the howling of an Iriſh Wolf, or the barking of an Iriſh Wolf dog does the Moon.</p>
            <p>The laſt Chronologicall obſervation (I perceive) troubles them exceedingly, and that is, the downfal of their Dagon, the Croſſe in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> which in baſe railing language he utters thus; <hi>Since Cheap-ſide Croſſe was pulled downe, the third of May</hi> 1643. <hi>and immediatly after all other Croſſes from off the top of Steeples in and about London, by a crew of Antichriſtian Parliamentary Round-heads, enemies to Chriſtianiſme,</hi> 3 yeers. Indeed it would trouble any Saint, any Chriſtian, any Heathen to loſe his God, or have his God taken from him, or his God forſake him; but for a wooden ſtone, golden, ſilver, leaden, iron gilt god, a headleſſe, mouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, earleſſe, noſeleſſe, handleſſe, footleſſe god; is none but a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical, ſenſleſſe Iriſh Man-Apian, or a meer man that hath as much underſtanding as an Ape, would be troubled at it; I doe much admire at this third day of <hi>May,</hi> as at any day in all the yeer; the Papiſts, Iriſh, and all Romaniſts, &amp;c. celebrate the third of <hi>May</hi> as a great Feſtivall, in commemoration that the Croſſe of Chriſt on which he ſuffered, was found about <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 326. on the third day of <hi>May,</hi> by <hi>Hellen</hi> Mother to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great, with the other two Croſſes (on which the two Thieves ſuffered) unperiſhed, as <hi>Ruffinus</hi> ſayes; and the third day of <hi>May</hi> is thus noted in the Almanack, <hi>Inventio Crucis:</hi> Saint <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſayes, the whole world is full of pieces of this Croſſe, and yet by a continuall miracle (as <hi>Paulinus</hi> ſaith) it hath never been impaired; and the County of <hi>Tipperary</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> is called <hi>The County of the holy Croſſe of Tipperary,</hi> and enjoys certain peculiar freedoms, granted in honour of a piece of Chriſts Croſſe, there ſometimes preſerved; thus were Chriſtians in ancient times per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113488:15"/> and incredible it is, what a confluence there is even yet of theſe ſottiſh, popiſh, Iriſh Manapians, continually upon devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thither, as unto an holy place, ſo firmly do they perſevere in the old, blind Religion of their fore-fathers, which the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe negligence of their Prelats, Biſhops and popiſh Prieſts and ignorance together, hath beyond all meaſure encreaſed, when as there be none to inſtruſt and teach them otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>It is true, that third of <hi>May,</hi> 1643. the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> was totally ſubverted and pulled down to the ground (yea, that morning <hi>Dagon</hi> was falled on his face to the ground, the head of <hi>Dagon</hi> and the palms of his hands were cut off, no not ſo much as the ſtump of <hi>Dagon</hi> was left unto him) by vertue of an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, and by the aſſiſtance of godly and honeſt men, friends to true Chriſtian Religion, but are enemies to, and have taken a Covenant to pluck up popery root and branch.) And not long after, the croſſes from off the top of many Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: Yes and in divers Churches and other places, many popiſh and ſuperſtitious pictures, croſſes, crucifixes and Romiſh Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, &amp;c. were demoliſhed, defaced and burnt; which are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fore-runners of the finall and utter deſtruction of <hi>Rome:</hi> Me thinks when I read <hi>Revelations</hi> the 18. I hear one crying mightily ſaying, <hi>Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul Spirit, and a Cage of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unclean and hatefull Bird, and therefore it is high time that we come out of her that we be not partakers of her ſinnes, and receive not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having briefly run over the Obſervations in the Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack, and thoſe others in the compendious Chronology of things memorable; I thought to have found in the Prognoſtick part thereof, ſome Oxonian Iriſh predictions againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> but God be thanked it is hid from their knowledge, and the evill they have wiſhed thereunto will redound and fall upon themſelves: There are ſome moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Obſervations touching planting, grafting, ſowing, and ſuch like affairs, &amp;c. but what they ſowe another ſhall reap, &amp;c. now in the concluſion of all, as if he were a profound calculator, an Aſtronomer indeed, he ſays, there will be three Eclipſes, two of the Sun, and one of the Moon, but none of them to be ſeen; Only
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113488:16"/> he doubts that of the Moon the 17. of <hi>July;</hi> I will put him out of doubt, and doe tell him, that there are five Eclipſes this yeer <hi>viz.</hi> three of the Sun, and two of the Moon, whereof only one of the Moon viſible in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that is already paſt; which was on Wedneſday the 21. of <hi>January</hi> laſt, about ſix of the clock in the morning, the beginning thereof being about four of the clock in the morning, I my ſelf ſaw; but immediatly after, by reaſon of a very thick miſt and foggy vapour, the light of the Moon, and viſibility of the Stars was taken away from us about <hi>London,</hi> that it could not be obſerved; this Eclipſe this Iriſh Manapian takes no notice of, as if there were not ſuch a one to be ſeen in the Heavens; but I ſhall tell him, it belongs to them, and the beſt of their friends; the effects begins now to operate; ſome ſhort Obſervations I have made in my Almanack of this yeer, to which I refer you: As for the reſt of the Eclipſes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard none of them are to be ſeen in any part of the Chriſtian world, I will not mention them; only I ſaid I will put him out of doubt: And again, doe tell him, that the Lunar Eclipſe the 17. of <hi>July</hi> next, ſhall not be ſeen in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> much leſſe in <hi>Ireland;</hi> for the beginning thereof will be about three quarters of an hour paſt one of the clock in the afternoon, the middle about five of the clock, and the end about ſeven of the clock, all which time, for the moſt part of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Moon is under the earth, and the Sun gloriouſly ſhineth above the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon: Indeed the Inhabitants in <hi>Finland, Litvania</hi> and <hi>Muſcovia</hi> ſhall obſerve the Moon to riſe Eclipſed; and they that live in <hi>Kirkithay,</hi> a Country in <hi>Tartary,</hi> in <hi>Turchestan,</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> within and without <hi>Ganges,</hi> and in the Gulf of <hi>Bengala,</hi> and in <hi>Sumatra,</hi> and places neer thereto, ſhall have that Eclipſe in their Miridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or midnight-ſted: But thoſe that are in <hi>Anian</hi> and <hi>Quivira,</hi> ſhall have the Moon to ſet Eclipſed; now for that the Sun is above the Horizon when this Eclipticall full Moon happeneth, being the 17. of <hi>July;</hi> and becauſe the Eclipſe is paſt when the Sun ſetteth, the Moon then riſing: There is no ſuch doubt to be made as this Iriſh Almanack would poſſeſſe his Country-men withall, notwithanding that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> amongſt many other places, ſhall partake of the effects of that Eclipſe, and of ſome others as well Lunar as Solar, lately paſſed, whoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113488:16"/> effects now moſt ſtrongly operate, together with a notable Conjunction of the two Malignant Planets <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> which happeneth this yeer on Friday the 12. of <hi>June,</hi> forty minutes paſt ſeven of the clock in the afternoon, in the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 17. degree and a half, and latitude 53. degrees and a half, agreeing neereſt to that of <hi>Dublin,</hi> being the chief City in <hi>Ireland;</hi> the poſition of the Heavens there at that time, being as followeth:</p>
            <figure>
               <head>A Coniuction of Staturne &amp; Mars on friday the 12 of Iune 1646 at Dublin in Ireland</head>
               <figDesc>figure contains many astrological symbols in addition to text</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>IN the yeer 1419. there was a Quadrate Aſpect of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn, Mars</hi> in the latter degrees of <hi>Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> in the latter degrees of <hi>Leo,</hi> the ſuppoſed Sign under which <hi>Bohemia,</hi> among many other places is; and there was that yeer, on the 26. day of <hi>March,</hi> a little before noon, a great Eclipſe of the Sun in the 15. degree of ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> ♂ <hi>Mars</hi> being governour thereof: After which followed a great tumult in <hi>Bohemia; Joannes Ziska,</hi> a noble Captain, and a man deſcended from a great Family, one very ingenuous and skilfull in Military Affairs, favouring the <hi>Huſſites,</hi> being ſore grieved for the death of <hi>John Hus</hi> and <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erom</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> raiſed a mighty Army, to the number of 40000. whom he called <hi>Thaborites;</hi> almoſt poſſeſt himſelf of all <hi>Bohemia,</hi> ſubverted the Monaſteries and Idolatrous Temples, pulling down, and breaking in pieces the Images and Idols, driving away the Prieſts and Monks, which he ſaid were kept up in their Cloyſters, like Swine in their Styes, to be fatted: His Army en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and in the yeer 1421. (having loſt before one of his eyes) loſt his other eye by a Shaft, when he beſieged the Town of <hi>Raby,</hi> but from hence being carried to <hi>Prague,</hi> was cured of his wounds, and would not (though he was blind) forſake his Army; and the next yeer defeateth the Emperour, and was <hi>Victor</hi> in many battles againſt the <hi>Pontificians;</hi> and in the yeer 1424. he was ſtriken with ſickneſſe, and dying, he gave order that a Drum ſhould be made of his skin, to terrifie the enemy. Now others ſuppoſe that Kingdom to be under ♋ <hi>Cancer,</hi> becauſe that in the yeer 1424. there was a great Eclipſe of the Sun the 26. day of <hi>June,</hi> in the 14. degree of <hi>Cancer,</hi> in the evening; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects ſucceeded the next yeer, <hi>viz.</hi> 1425. at what time three pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113488:17"/> Armies from <hi>Saxony, Franconia</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> entred into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in three ſeverall places, but they all fled without ſight of an enemy, and left their Tents to the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner <hi>Saxony</hi> and the maritine Cities neer there, are ſuppoſed to be under the Sign ♑ <hi>Capricorn,</hi> becauſe after ſome great Eclipſe or unfortunate Aſpects of the ſuperiour Planets being in the ſame afflicted, ſome notable calamity hath happened thereunto; ſo in the yeer 1548. there was a Conjunction of ♄ <hi>Saturn</hi> and ♂ <hi>Mars,</hi> in ♑ <hi>Capricorn,</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> foreſhewing the many troubles that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſoon after in <hi>Saxony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo the City of <hi>Venice</hi> is ſaid to be ſubject to the Sign ♋ <hi>Cancer,</hi> for that many wonderfull events have happened to that City, when an Eclipſe or great Aſpect of the ſuperiour Planets hath happened in that Sign, or in the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> Quadrate or ☍ Oppoſite Aſpect thereof; ſo in the time of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> the firſt Emperour in <hi>Germany,</hi> 1505. who made peace with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> (there was a ☌ Conjunction of the higher Plante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi>) they were extreamly put to it, and ſuffered much by him, and he by them: And 1508. the Emperour, Pope and the French, enter in League at <hi>Cambray</hi> againſt the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the next yeer after, they took divers places in <hi>Forum Julij,</hi> and other places from the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and in few yeers after, ſtrange tranſactions of Affairs happened between the Pope and them; the French and them ſometimes on one ſide, ſometimes on the other, as Hiſtorians relate.</p>
            <p>In like manner the famous City of <hi>Noremberg</hi> (amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others) although the time is uncertain of the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, yet from notable events, and admirable, unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all accidents which have happened unto the ſame, it is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conjectured to be under the Sign II <hi>Gemini,</hi> for when a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Conjunction happened in ♍ <hi>Virgo,</hi> which doth afflict the Sign II <hi>Gemini</hi> by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> Quadrate, and ☿ <hi>Mercury</hi> be unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, then ſome ominous matter hath happened thereunto; and ſo likewiſe if any Eclipſe be in the ſaid Signs, as in the yeer 1448. the 29. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was an Eclipſe of the Sun, in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113488:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113488:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113488:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113488:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113488:20"/> 15. degree of ♍ <hi>Virgo,</hi> in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> Quadrate to ♊ <hi>Gemini,</hi> with whom ♄ <hi>Saturn</hi> mixed his malicious influence; <hi>Marchio Albertus,</hi> Sir-named the <hi>Achilles</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> fought nine battles with the <hi>Norembergers,</hi> and was <hi>Victor</hi> in eight of them, with great deſtruction to the Citizens.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe in the yeer 1551. was a great Eclipſe of the Sun in 17. degrees of ♍ <hi>Virgo,</hi> ♂ <hi>Mars</hi> being elevated in the middle of Heaven, above the Eclipſe, but placed in his Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ♎ <hi>Libra;</hi> a little while after which, <hi>Albertus Marchio,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Caſimir,</hi> beſieged the City, the Suburbs were ſpoiled and the Citizens were compelled to diſhonourable conditions of peace.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe in the yeer 1560. another Eclipſe of the Sun happened in the eighth degree of ♍ <hi>Virgo,</hi> in Quadrate to ♊ <hi>Gemini;</hi> in which Sign of <hi>Gemini,</hi> ♄ <hi>Saturn</hi> was in 22. degrees very much afflicting ☿ <hi>Mercury,</hi> who was Lord of the ſaid Eclipſe in 22. degrees of <hi>Virgo;</hi> by which means the evil fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewn by the Eclipſe, was duplicated, or much encreaſed, and the effects continued to the yeer 1563. in which ſpace of time many thouſands of the <hi>Norembergers</hi> were ſwept away with the plague.</p>
            <p>I might reckon up many other places which Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians make mention of, but I ſhall much exceed my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I will only remember ſome few Obſervations concerning <hi>England;</hi> and all or moſt Aſtrologers think it to be under the Sign ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> for that when any Eclipſe or great Conjunction happeneth in that Sign, or the oppoſite Sign ♎ <hi>Libra,</hi> or the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> Quadrate Signes, ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> or ♑ <hi>Capricorn,</hi> ſome memorable occurence hath befallen that Kingdom; as in the yeer 1345. there was a totall Eclipſe of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> Moon the 18. day of <hi>March</hi> about 9. of the clock in the night, in the 6. degree of ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> oppoſite to ♈ <hi>Aries;</hi> in which yeer, ſuch unuſuall tempeſts, and violent winds, with great rains and inundations happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the whole Summer, and likewiſe in the time of Harveſt, that in the Northern parts Corn, and alll manner of Grain and fruits were corrupted and putrified, and for two yeers following, was a great ſcarcity of all things, and much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113488:20"/> famine, and a great mortality amongſt Sheep: And in the yeer 1346. the 28. day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was a moſt terrible battle fought between <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Valoys,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King of <hi>England,</hi> at <hi>Creſſe,</hi> where the Engliſh with 10000. men, overcame 60000. French; the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was there ſlain, together with 30000, men, 11. Princes, 89. Barons, and 1200. Knights; and in the yeer 1347. King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> winneth <hi>Calice, John Copland</hi> defeateth the Scots, takes <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> priſoner, who is ſent to the Tower; <hi>Copland</hi> was made a Banneret, and rewarded with 500 <hi rend="sup">li</hi>. <hi>per annum;</hi> and in the yeer 1348. was ſuch a mortality and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence amongſt men, as ſcarce hath been known the like, 50000 were buried in the Charter-houſe Church-yard; and many ſtrange matters happened in thoſe times, which our Hiſtories and Chronicles mention, to which I refer you.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe I will remember that terrible Eclipſe of the Sun, which was on the ſecond day of <hi>October,</hi> 1605. about one of the clock in the afternoon, in the 19. degree of ♎ <hi>Libra,</hi> being the oppoſite Sign to ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> under which <hi>England</hi> is ſuppoſed to be ſubject: What a horrible, unheard of, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſon of the Papiſts was diſcovered the 5. of <hi>November</hi> following, I hope will never be forgotten in <hi>England:</hi> If I ſhould but remember the Eclipſe of the Sun which happened on Friday the 29. of <hi>March</hi> 1633. in the 19. degree of ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> I ſhould be over-tedious, I will refer you to my Almanack for that yeer and ſome yeers following, in which the tyranny of the Prelats in theſe times manifeſtly appearing, I my ſelfe not eſcaping their fury; So alſo that Eclipſe of the Moon the 8. of <hi>Octo.</hi> 1641. in the 26. degree of <hi>Aries:</hi> or that of the Moon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the 4. of <hi>April</hi> 1642. in 25. degrees of ♎ <hi>Libra,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Moon the 27. of <hi>September</hi> following, in the 15. degrees of ♈ <hi>Aries;</hi> or that of the Moon likewiſe the 17. of <hi>September</hi> 1643. in 4. degrees of ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> I ſhould but rub the gold horſe back, and put your in mind of the ſad and deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition (too freſh in our memory) this poor Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is in.</p>
            <p>I will ſet down theſe following Tables, wherein you may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113488:21"/> underſtand unto what Signes Aſtologers have placed (out of continuall obſervation and experience) many Countries and Cities, that thereby you may ſee when any Eclipſe of the Sun or Moon, or notable Conjunction or Configuration of the ſuperiour Planets happeneth, what places are ſubject or like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to participiate of the influence of any ſuch Coeleſtiall poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under ſuch Signes, their ☍ oppoſite and <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> Quadrate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; theſe Signs following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aries,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♈</seg> 
               <hi>Taurus,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♉</seg> 
               <hi>Gemini,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♊</seg> 
               <hi>Cancer,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♋</seg> 
               <hi>Virgo,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♍</seg> Is oppoſite to <hi>Libra,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♎</seg> 
               <hi>Scorpio,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♏</seg> 
               <hi>Sagitary,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♐</seg> 
               <hi>Capricorn,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♑</seg> 
               <hi>Aquary,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♒</seg> 
               <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♓</seg> 
            </p>
            <p>And this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect is an aſpect of perfect enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and hatred; and this is ſix Signs aſunder.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe theſe Signs following doe behold one another, though not ſo violently, yet they doe diſagree very much in Nature and diſpoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> by a Quadrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aries,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♈</seg> 
               <hi>Taurus,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♉</seg> 
               <hi>Gemini,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♊</seg> 
               <hi>Cancer,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♋</seg> 
               <hi>Leo,</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♌</seg> 
               <hi>Virgo.</hi>
               <seg rend="above">♍</seg> Hath a Quadrate Aſpect to ♋♑—♌♒—♍♓—♎♈—♉♏—♊♐. </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Aries</hi> beholds <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> by a Quadrate <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>; <hi>Taurus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Aquary; Gemini</hi> beholds <hi>Virgo</hi> and <hi>Piſces; Cancer</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Aries; Leo</hi> beholds <hi>Taurus</hi> and <hi>Scorpio;</hi> and <hi>Virgo</hi> beholds <hi>Gemini</hi> and <hi>Sagittary,</hi> by a Quadrate Aſpect, which is called an Aſpect of imperfect emnity, or faigned friendſhip, or trecherous amity, &amp;c. and this is three Signs aſunder.</p>
            <p>But there is another manner of the Signs beholding one another, two wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> by a Trine Aſpect, which is an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of perfect amity and friendſhip, and is when Signs of one Triplicity of Nature behold one another: As
<list>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113488:21"/>
                  <item>♈ ♌ ♐ are of the fiery Triplicity, hot and dry.</item>
                  <item>♉ ♍ ♑ are of the earthly Triplicicy, cold and dry.</item>
                  <item>♊ ♎ ♒ are of the aiery Triplicity, hot and moiſt.</item>
                  <item>♋ ♏ ♓ are of the watry Triplicity, cold and moiſt.</item>
               </list> Thus we ſee the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonagrees with the earthly Triplicity in drineſſe, and with the Aery in heat; and the earthly triplicity agrees with the watery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity in coldneſſe, and with the fiery triplicity in drineſſe, <hi>&amp; ſic è converſo.</hi> Theſe three Signes doe behold one another by a trine <g ref="char:trine">△</g> aſpect; and for the moſt part when any of the ſignes of one nature is well qualified or affected, by a certain ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and agreement, the other ſignes of the ſame qualitie participates of the ſame good or evlll influence: and this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect is foure Signes aſunder.</p>
            <p>The other Aſpect is called a ⚹ Sextile, and is more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then the Trine: and the Signes doe thus behold one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>♈ ♉ ♊ ♋ ♌ ♍ <hi>Hath a Sextile aſpect to</hi> ♒♊—♓♋—♈♌—♉♍—♊♎—♋♏</p>
            <p>Here we ſee the fiery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity agrees with the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in heat, the Earthy with the Watery in coldneſſe; the Aery with the Fiery in heat, and the Watery with the Earthy in coldneſſe by a ⚹ A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: and this is when Planets or Starres are two ſignes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall ſet downe the twelve Zodiacall Signs, and ſuch places, Kingdomes, Countries and Cities as have experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally been found to have been ſubject to the ſaid Signes: and they are as followeth:</p>
            <list>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>England North and Eaſt part, France, Germany, Suevia, Sileſia the higher, part of Polonia, Burgundie, part of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Baſternia, Syria, Paleſtine.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Naples, Capua, Ancona, Ferrara, Florence, Verona, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamo,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113488:22"/> Lindaw, Trajectum, Padua, Marſeilles, Epidaurum, Crackow, Auguſta Caeſarea, Vincentia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♉ <hi>Taurus</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Ruſſia, Polonia the great, the North part of Sweathland, IRELAND, Lorraigne, Campania, Helvetia, Rhetia, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia, Parthia, Perſia, the Iſlands Cyclades between Europe and Aſia, Cyprus, the Sea towns of Aſia the leſſe.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Bononia, Sena, Mantua, Tarentum, Panorme in Sicily, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſium, Parma, Caput Hiſtriae, Brixia, Tigure, Lucerne, Nantz, Metis, Herbipolis, Carolſtade, Liepſig, Poſnania, Gneſna, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagrade.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♊ <hi>Gemini,</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Sardinia, part of Lumbardy, South &amp; Weſt part of England, part of Flanders, Brabant, the Dukedome of Wittemberge, Hircania, Armenia, Mariana, Cyreniaca, Marmarica, Aegypt the Lower.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♊ <hi>Gemini,</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Carduba in Spaine, Viterbiurn, Coeſena a City in Lumbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Turin, Vercelli, Rhegium, Lovaine, Bruges in Flaunders, LONDON, Mentz, Kitzing, Hasford, Bamberge, Villacum, Noremberge, though Schoner and Cardan ſay it is under Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitary, yet Garcaeus proves it for many reaſons to be under Gemini.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>SCOTLAND, Granado, part of Burgundy, HOLLAND, Zeland, Pruſſia, Numidia, Africa, Bithynia, Phrygia, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis, Carthage.</item>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113488:22"/>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Conſtantinople, Tunis, VENICE, Genoa, Lucas, Piſa, Millain, Vincentia, Bern, YORK, Saint ANDREWES in SCOTLAND, Lubeck, Magdeburge, Wittenburgh, Gorlick,</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♌ <hi>Leo</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Gallia Togata, being part of Lumbardy, the Alps, Italy, Sicyly, Apulia, Bohemia (but <hi>Garcius</hi> thinks it to be under ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi>) part of Turky, Aemilia, Sabina, Phaenicia, Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, Orchinia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♌ <hi>Leo</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Damaſco, Siracuſa, ROME, Ravenna, Cremona, Ulms, Confluence, Prague, Lintz, Cremuſium.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♍ <hi>Virgo</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Achaia, Greece, Creet, Croacia, Carinthia, Artheſina, the Dukedom of Athens, Meſopotamia, Babylon, Aſſyria, part of Gallia Comata, part of Rhyne, Syleſia the lower.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♍ <hi>Virgo</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Hieruſalem, Corinth, Rhodes, Papia or Pavia, Sigina, Brunduſium, Cuma a City in Campania, Aretium or Arezzo, Novaria a City in Italy, Tholouſe, Lyons, Paris, Bazil, Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg, Erphord, Uratiſlavia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Auſtria, Alſatia, Livonia, Savoy, Daulphine, Bactriana, Toſcanye, Caſpia, Seres in Aethiopia, Thebaida, Oaſis a Country in Aegypt called Azagar, Trogloditica a Country in Aethiopia, Sundgavia.</item>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113488:23"/>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Lisbone, Arles, Gajetta in Italy, Lauda a City in Maurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Sueſſa, Placentia, Felkirk, Friberge, or Carda Bianca, Argentina, Spiers, Frankford ad Maenum, Hala in Suevia, Winpina, Heilbrunna, Friſinga, Moſpachium, Landshut, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna in Auſtria, Anwerp.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♏ <hi>Scorpio</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>NORWAY, Bavaria the upper, Metagonitis now called Biledulgerid in Numidia, a Region in Affrica, Comogena a Country in Syria, Cappadocia, Idumea, Mauritania, Fes, Gethulia, Catalonia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♏ <hi>Scorpio</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Algiers, Valentia in Spain, Trabezond, Urbine, Aquilegia, Piſtorium, Camerinum, Tareciſium, Forum Julium, Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Vienna Allabrogum, Aichſtade, Monachum, Gedanum, Frankfod upon Oder.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♐ <hi>Sagittary</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>SPAIN, Dalmatia, Sclavonia, Hungary, Moravia, Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Geltica, Thyrrenia, Arabia the happy.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♐ <hi>Sagittary</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Toledo in Spain, Volaterra a City in Hetruria, Mutina, Narbon, Avenion, Colonia Agrippina, or Colen, Studgard, Rottenburg, Judenburg, Buda, Gaſcovia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♑ <hi>Capricorn</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Macedonia, Illiria, Thracia, Boſſina, Albania, Bulgaria,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113488:23"/> part of Greece, Maſovia, Litvania, Saxony, Haſſia, Thurin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, Marchia in Styria, the Iſlands of the Orchades, India, Arriana, Gedrofia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♑ <hi>Capricorn</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>OXFORD, Mechlin, Juliacum, Clevonia, Berga, Gaunt, Vilna, Brandenburge, Auguſta Vindelicorum, or Ausburg, Conſtance, Derthona, Faventia.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♒ <hi>Aquary</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Amazonia, Sarmatia, Tartaria the great, Wallachia, Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covia, Swethland the South part, Denmark part, Weſtpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Moſell, Piemont, Bavaria part, Aethiopia, Sogdiana, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Arabia the deſert and ſtony.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♒ <hi>Aquary</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Hamborough, Breme, Mountferate, Piſaurum, Trent, Saltz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Ingolſtade.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♓ <hi>Piſces</hi> theſe Countries.</label>
               <item>Cilicia, Calabria, Portugall, Galitia, Normandy, Phaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Naſamonia in Lybia, Garamantes, Lydia, Pamphilia, Aegypt the higher.</item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ♓ <hi>Piſces</hi> theſe Cities.</label>
               <item>Alexandria, Hiſpalis Compoſtella, Parentium, Rhemes, Wormes, Ratiſpone, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now having ſhewn what Signs are appropriated to certain places, and what places Ancient and Modern Aſtronomers have in many reſpects found ſubject to the influence of the ſaid Signs, which hath its ground from the like reaſons as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113488:24"/> are experimented in Nativities; for as when any terrible E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of (the Luminaries) the Sun or Moon ſhall be in the Aſcendant of any man or woman, in the mid-heaven, or the part of fortune thereof, or in the oppoſite or Quadrate place to any of theſe in the Nativity; or when any of the infortunes or malignant Planets, <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> ſhall paſſe by any of thoſe places, or ſhall aſpect any of them hatefully, it threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens deſtruction or death, or ſome eminent danger, or evill ſucceſſe in affairs to ſuch a man or woman, eſpecially if any evill direction ſhall happen at or neere the time of ſuch Eclipſe, Conjunction, Aſpect or Tranſit; and of the truth of this, innumerable examples might be given: So likewiſe thoſe Kingdoms or Countries, Cities or places that have any fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with the Sign wherein the Eclipſe doth happen, or in that wherein any notable Conjunction or other great Aſpect is, for the moſt part they have had grievous and ſore afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and troubles, as I could inſtance in many examples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what I have ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall proceed to ſome obſervations touching the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 14. degree 27. minutes or <hi>Taurus,</hi> both of them culminating with that fatall Star <hi>Caput Algol,</hi> or the head of <hi>Meduſa,</hi> ſo ominous to, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truncating ſome great perſonages heretofore, and no leſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious to others now living, who if they had ſome faithfull <hi>Spurina</hi> about them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spurina</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall day to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar</hi> the Ides of March</note> to tell them of their iminent danger, might perhaps, if not prevent, yet mittigate that evill influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence impending, or otherwiſe being forewarned, might be the better provided againſt an inevitable ſtorm; but not to meddle with particulars (only I could wiſh men were more obſerving of the true time, or neereſt that can be of their nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities, together with ſome Accidents (as impriſonment, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſickneſſe, &amp; many other caſualties incident to man kind) for the verification thereof, which I have given notice of in many of my Almanacks heretofore) I will therefore come to the generals of this Conjunction; and as I ſaid before, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth on Friday the 12. of <hi>June</hi> 1646. 40. minutes paſt 7. of the clock in the afternoon, in the Meridian of <hi>Dublin;</hi> it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113488:24"/> in the fourth houſe, two degrees diſtant from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Venus,</hi> who ſome three days before, <hi>viz.</hi> the 9. of <hi>June</hi> is corporally with <hi>Saturn,</hi> declining <hi>Mars,</hi> whom ſhe finds ſo debilitated, as if ſhe had no mind to conjoin with him; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are peregrine, that is, out of all dignities; and when any Planet is ſo, he is as it were a man deprived of all he hath, or ſequeſtred from his eſtate; and unleſſe the neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Venus</hi> by her corporal preſence, and the Sextile Aſpect of <hi>Jupiter</hi> to them both, doth abate of their evil poſiture, it is a very ill meeting of them to thoſe places and people they have influence upon, which are under <hi>Taurus, Scorpio, Aquary,</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> with is the ſecond Quadrangle of the Zodiaque, and moſt concerned in this Conjunction, which happens in <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the night houſe of <hi>Venus,</hi> where ſhe her ſelf is, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently well fortified and irradiated, and doth ſeparate apace from theſe two malevolents; yet the Moon (who conveys the influence of all the heavenly bodies upon all ſublunary crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) hath more to doe in the ſaid Conjunction then <hi>Venus,</hi> for it is her exaltation, and ſhe hath a triplicity and face therein; but if we obſerve how unfortunately ſhee is placed in the very degree of her fall; for as ſhee is exalted in three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Taurus,</hi> ſo ſhe is abaſed and caſt down in three degrees of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> in which ſhe now is exactly, and is placed in the tenth houſe, which is the houſe of Rule and Dominion, Kings, Princes, &amp;c. the poſition will hold, whether it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſo the Scheam will ſerve the three Kingdoms; and <hi>Mars</hi> who diſpoſeth the place of the Moon, and the moſt part of the mid-heaven, is in his Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the oppoſite houſe; and the next day, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> having been in a friendly Trine to the Sun, meeting the like Aſpect, from <hi>Jupiter</hi> imniediatly fals into the oppoſition, a moſt hatefull Aſpect of <hi>Saturn, Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus, Quando Planeta eſt in Aſpectu ſui hostis, eſt ut vir timens hostem ſuum;</hi> that is, when a Planet is Aſpected of his enemy, he is as a man that is afraid of his foe; and ſuch is the condition of the Moon now; <hi>Quando eſt cum hoste ſuo, eſt ut virpugnans cum hoste ſuo;</hi> that is, when a Planet is Aſpected of his enemy, he fights with his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113488:25"/> foe; ſo is the Moon now, having two malicious enemies; <hi>Quando eſt cadens a domo ſua, vel a domo exaltationis ſuae, eſt ut vit abſens a domo ſua, aut Civitate ſua;</hi> that is, when a Planet fals from his houſe or exaltation, he is as a man abſent from his houſe or City; ſo are <hi>Mars</hi> and the Moon now; <hi>Quando Planeta eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, eſt ut vir vexatus &amp; timidus,</hi> he is as a man vexed and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo are <hi>Mars</hi> and the Moon at this time; <hi>Planeta in domo non ſua, eſt ut vir in domo aliena pulſans, jam deprimitur judicium ſuum, nec eſt ei authoritas;</hi> a Planet that is not in his houſe, is as a man knocking at another mans door, his judgment is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and is without authority; ſo are <hi>Saturn, Mars</hi> and the Moon now; <hi>Ex Centiloquis Bethem,</hi> 10, 11, 14, 18, 27. <hi>cum duo infortunae conjunguntur &amp; Luna congruit cum Saturno in latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, erit fames &amp; mortalitas;</hi> that is, when the two infortunes are conjoyned, and the Moon ſhall agree in latitude with <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> there ſhall be famine and mortality; <hi>Si vero Marti muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur Reges, &amp; erit multa ſanguinis effuſio, &amp; praelia in loco qui ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur ab ipſo ſigno, &amp; hoc non fallit, propoſitio Almanſoris</hi> 132. that is, if the Moon ſhall agree with <hi>Mars</hi> in latitude, Kings ſhall change, and there ſhall be much effuſion of blood, and great wars ſhall be in that place ſignified by that Sign: And this fails not, indeed the Moon hath five degrees, <hi>Saturn</hi> two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees fourteen minutes, and <hi>Mars</hi> but 46. minutes, all of them having South latitude; the Moon agreeth neereſt with <hi>Saturn</hi> thougn their latitude is of one kind, <hi>viz.</hi> South: But I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the whole Aphoriſme will be in force, and not any part thereof mittigated, notwithſtanding the interpoſition of thoſe friendly beams of the Sun and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion are very weak, and not able to effect or procure that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected relief and aſſiſtance to theſe Tauriſts and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guido Bonatus,</hi> in <hi>parte</hi> 4. <hi>Astronomiae,</hi> fol. 556. cap. 66. ſays, <hi>Cum fuerit Saturnus in Tauro, fueritque in Angulo directus, ſignificat contentiones &amp; bella, &amp;c.</hi> that is, if <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall be in <hi>Taurus</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in an Angle, he ſignifies contentions and wars: And <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humaſar</hi> ſays, there ſhall be tribulations and injuries, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings and Earthquakes, the deſtruction of Cities, Towns
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113488:25"/> and Houſes; and <hi>Guido</hi> ſays of <hi>Mars, in Capite</hi> 86. fol. 572. <hi>Si fuerit in Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro ſignificat ventos validos venturos, &amp; destructionem fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, ſimiliter &amp; Arborum &amp; hoc ex cauſa Caloris excedentis debitum &amp; naturalem modum, ſignificat etiam multitudinem nubium atque nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilarum; pluviarum quoque ac tonitruorum &amp; fulgurum;</hi> that is, if <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall be in <hi>Taurus,</hi> he ſignifies very ſtrong winds, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of fruits, and alſo of Trees, and this to proceed from an undue and diſproportioned heat, exceeding its naturall temper and conſtitution; alſo very cloudy weather, with abundance of rain, thunder and lightning; <hi>Albumaſar</hi> ſays, <hi>ſignificat mortem mulierum &amp; Vaccarum, &amp; ſignificat bella ventura inter Cives Orientis &amp; Cives Occidentis;</hi> that is, it foreſheweth to death of Women and Kyne, and that there ſhall be war between the Citizens (people) of the Eaſt, and thoſe of the Weſt: <hi>Haly parte octava de Juditiis Astrorum</hi> cap. 7. ſays, <hi>Si Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnus in quarta domo fuerit, &amp; ibi malificus, ſignificat quod res &amp; aedificia cadent, minuentur plantationes, abſcindentur aquae, &amp; erit in populo diminutio, &amp; paupertas, &amp; gens illius Climatis erit obſeſſa, &amp; non audebunt exire de ſuis villis propter timorem inimicorum fuorum; quod eo fortius erit &amp; magis affixum, ſi quarta domus fuerit Signum fixum, quia tunc erit damnum fortius &amp; durabilius;</hi> that is, if <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall be in the fourth houſe, and be there malevolent, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houſes &amp; buildings ſhal fal, come to decay and periſh, planting or ſeting ſhall be diminiſhed, waters cut off, the people ſhall be leſſened or abated, there ſhall be poverty to them, and people of that Country ſhall be obſeſſed or beſieged, they ſhall not dare to goe out of their Towns (Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Caſtles or Countries) by reaſon of the fear they ſhall have of their enemies; and this ſhall be more affixed (certain) if the fourth houſe ſhall be a fixed Sign, and the hurt (dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage) or loſſe, ſhall be more ſtrong and durable: This Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme agrees exactly with the poſition of the malignant Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net <hi>Saturn</hi> at this time in every reſpect: Furthermore <hi>Haly</hi> ſayes, <hi>in parte</hi> 8. <hi>de Juditiis Astrorum</hi> cap. 25. <hi>Si quando Mars junctus fuerit cum Saturno ſtruet quilibet alteri fraudes, &amp; deceptiones &amp; erunt inter homines percuſſiones &amp; vulnera, etiam accidet regi impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentum &amp; labor ab homine qui eſt de terra parittionis illius ſigni in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113488:26"/> quo junguntur;</hi> that is, if <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall be conjoined, one man ſhall ſeek to entrap another, there ſhall be many fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and deceits, much woundings, fightings and quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and impediment danger and trouble ſhall happen to the King, from a man which is of that Countrey under the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Signe: And a little after, in fol. 392. <hi>Si applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Lunae cum Saturno fuerit adecima per oppoſitionem Accident Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Populis placita &amp; diſcordiae, &amp; Capientur multi de populis prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcordiam Regum cum ipſis, &amp; propter magnum metum quem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent de eis.</hi> If he application of the Moone to Saturne ſhall be by oppoſition from the tenth houſe, there ſhall be many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and differences happen to the King and People; and many of that People, by reaſon of ſuch differences between them ſhall be captived or taken, through the great feare they ſhall have of them. The ſum of all theſe Aphoriſmes amounts to thus much, That in regard at the time of this Conjunction the mid heaven is ſo extreamely afflicted, and <hi>Mars</hi> Lord thereof, which is ſignificator of men in greateſt authority, whether they be Kings, Princes, Lords, or other great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Potentates, whether they be of the Families and race of the <hi>O's</hi> or <hi>Mac's,</hi> who ſo domineer and Lord it with their Galloglaſſes and Kernes in <hi>Ireland;</hi> or whether we take our judgement from the Moon, who is ſignificatrix of the People there ſo miſerably poſited, I cannot pronounce other then ruine and deſtruction to thoſe great ones, ſubverſion of their ancient Families, and ruine to their ſtately Buildings, Cities, Townes. Towers and Caſtles. That People ſhall be in moſt miſerable and deplorable condition. We ſee the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction is in <hi>Taurus,</hi> under which, amongſt other places, <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is poſited; and that the ſignes <hi>Leo, Scorpio</hi> and <hi>Aquary,</hi> are ſharers, and muſt participate in this influence; Famine, Scarcity, Plagues and terrible warfare ſhall happen to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places under thoſe Signes. If they expect ayd from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne parts, they will be fruſtrated; Me thinkes I behold all the States of Europe involv'd in this Quarrell; the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> Matching, the Hollander buſie, the POPE thundering his Bulls and Excommunications,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113488:26"/> the <hi>Turke</hi> making great preparations, ſo likewiſe the <hi>Germane, Dane, Swede, Polonian, Venetian,</hi> nay what State in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World is not diſquieted? If I ſhould recount the Eclipſes and great Conjunctions of the ſuperior Planets in Signes, to which moſt or all Countries in <hi>Europe</hi> are ſubjected, and the events that have ſucceeded within theſe few yeares in theſe places, I might rather make an Hiſtory then a ſuccinct diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; there were not long ſince two or three Eclipſes of both the <hi>Luminaryes</hi> in the Signe <hi>Leo,</hi> the effects of all which are ſtrongly operating, and for many yeares together will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce admirable and unexpected occurrences, I believe the progreſſe of <hi>Saturne</hi> through the Signe <hi>Taurus,</hi> out of which he will not fully free himſelfe till the end of <hi>March</hi> 1648. will be very fatall to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and moſt chiefely he will powre out his influence upon that place rather then any other; For if we conſider the preſent condition thereof, ſince the Rebellion there broke forth, The horrid Murthers, and cruell ſlaughters by them committed upon many thouſands of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, whoſe bloud cryes for vengeance, doe authoriſe me <hi>Aſtrologically</hi> to pronounce a fearefull doome of Fire, Sword, Plague, and Famine to follow that bloudy Nation, Let me tell the <hi>Spaniard, French,</hi> or what other Nation ſoever that is ayding or aſſiſting them, they muſt not eſcape the Divine vengeance which God by the Starres, his Coeleſtiall Miniſters doth me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace them withall; If the <hi>Pope</hi> ſend his Agents to proſecute their Deſignes, he may chance looſe his Triple Crowne in this unjuſt quarrell they have raiſed. The Divell may rage for a ſeaſon, <hi>Sed ſi Deus nobiſcum quis contra nos,</hi> The fight from Heaven, the Starre in their Courſes fight againſt (CaesAR) <hi>Siſera;</hi> I hope I ſhall ſpeak truth, if I tell the <hi>French, Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> or any other friend, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> or their Aſſociates have, that though they never made greater preparations, yet with as like ſucceſſe as that Invincible <hi>Armado</hi> in 88 had, at what time foureſcore of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships were loſt with not ſo few as twenty thouſand men. The windes and Seas fighting at that time for <hi>England,</hi> which was many yeares before threatned by the proud and inſulting <hi>Spaniard;</hi> This <hi>Armado</hi> conſiſted of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113488:27"/> 130 Ships, nineteene thouſand two hundred and ninty Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, eight thouſand three hundred and fifty Mariners, two thouſand and foureſcore Gally-ſlaves, two thouſand ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty great Ordinance: which Navy having been three yeares in preparing (and at no ſmall charge) within one moneth was often beaten and at length put to flight, (and as I ſaid 20000 of their men being ſlaine, and not above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were miſſing) the remainder of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſome in their ſlight were caſt upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ireland,</hi> and thoſe few that eſcaped returned with a great deale of diſhonour into <hi>Spaine,</hi> above 700 Souldiers and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were caſt upon the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> ſhore, who were afterward ſent over to the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> but thoſe which by Tempeſt were driven upon <hi>Ireland</hi> found a harder meaſure, for the wild <hi>Iriſh</hi> of their owne accord ſlew many of them: I ſuppoſe their cruelty is not inferiour now to what it was then, but ſuppoſe the <hi>French, Spaniſh, Iriſh</hi> Jeſuite, Popiſh Fryer, Prieſt, and the whole rabble of <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> in all the World were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined together, againſt <hi>England,</hi> let but an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man name 1588. or 1605. And without doubt the proudeſt and moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elleſt of them all will be daunted, and ſink down with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo powerfull hath God ſhowne himſelfe in thoſe times. That in the firſt the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> himſelfe acknowledged the misfortune that befell him to have been the handy worke of God, and gave thanks to God and his Saints, (cauſing the like to be done throughout <hi>Spaine</hi>) that it fell to be no worſe. And for that in 1605 certainly it was the eye of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that diſcovered that horrid deed of darkneſſe, the <hi>Gun-Powder Treaſon</hi> invented by the Divelliſh Papiſts, to the deſtruction of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſo conſequently to the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Let us looke back to the yeare 1587. (In which yeare <hi>Mary</hi> Queene of <hi>Scots</hi> was beheaded) for the poſition of <hi>Saturne,</hi> and we ſhall finde that from the firſt of <hi>March</hi> that yeare, to the middle of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1589 he walked through <hi>Taurus,</hi> the Signe under which he now is &amp;c. under which <hi>Ireland</hi> is ſubjected as I ſaid before, In the moneth of <hi>August</hi> the 28 day was an
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113488:27"/> ominous oppoſition of <hi>Mars</hi> from <hi>Scorpio,</hi> to him in the 16 degree, and if we obſerve this memorable yeare 1588. Upon the 28 of <hi>May Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> were in Conjunction, in the 19 degrees <hi>Taurus</hi> not farre from the place they now meete in, not many dayes after which that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſt. If we examine our Chronicles we ſhall finde moſt Memorable Paſſages in divers parts of the World, to have happened this yeare: Was it not unuſuall and ſtrange, that <hi>Polonia</hi> this yeare ſhould have three Kings uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Title, while the fourth <hi>viz. Stephen Battori</hi> was yet unburied? Namely <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> the <hi>Sweden, Maximilian</hi> the Emperours brother, and <hi>Henry Valoys</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> of which three <hi>Maximilian</hi> in the beginning of this yeare was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner, his Army overthrowne by meanes thereof, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of men, women, and children, carryed away Captives by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> Thus ſaith <hi>Gallobelgicus,</hi> and further that <hi>Suetia</hi> was all on fire with tumults, and loſt certain places of ſtrength to the <hi>Muſcovite;</hi> The <hi>Muſcovite</hi> himſelfe ranne mad and loſt his wits. The King of <hi>Denmarke Frederick</hi> the ſecond dyed; In <hi>France</hi> the <hi>Barricados</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> the flight of the King from thence, The ſlaughter of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and his brother the Cardinall of <hi>Lorrayne;</hi> The death of the Queen Mother, the poyſoning of the Prince of <hi>Condee;</hi> and the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw which the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> gave unto Duke <hi>Mercury,</hi> (all which <hi>Les derniers troubles de Fraunce</hi> do teſtifie) and gave that Kingdome ſufficient cauſe to thinke that yeare 1588 to be an extraordinary yeere, At the ſame time the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> prepared his Army, and ſurprized <hi>Carmagmall,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> his chiefe Magazine in <hi>Saluze.</hi> The <hi>Turke</hi> ſuffered great overthrowes in <hi>Hungaria.</hi> And in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by reaſon of falſe moneys, wherewith the <hi>Jauizaryes</hi> were payd their wages, they fell into a Mutiny, and compelled the Emperour of the <hi>Turks</hi> to deliver unto them his chiefeſt Favourites to be put to death, and that likewiſe they might remove his Officers at their pleaſure, yet they were not coment herewith, they ſet fire on the <hi>Jewes</hi> Houſes, ſpoyled their goods, and by that meanes above twelve thouſand of their Houſes were burnt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113488:28"/> downe to the ground in the ſame City. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> were continually moleſted with the the incurſions of the <hi>Turkes;</hi> The Sophy of <hi>Perſia</hi> dyed. And (if I may uſe the words of <hi>Gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belgicu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) ab ortu Solis uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad occaſum, nullus firmè remanſit lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus in quo non miratu dignum aliquid hoc Anno contigerit.</hi> That is, from the riſing of the Sunne to the going downe thereof, there was ſcarce any place in which ſomething worthy Memory did not happen. This yeere <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> foretold, (a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death at <hi>Rome, viz.</hi> 1475. one hundreth and thirteen yeares before it came to paſſe) to his effect.</p>
            <p>The Tranſlation whereof as I have read in <hi>Dutch</hi> is thus.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tauſen funfhundert achtzitchtacht</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Das iſt das iar, das ich betracht,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Geth in dem de weltnixt under</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Geschicht doch groz merklich wunder.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poſt mille expletos a partu Virginis Annos,</l>
                  <l>Et poſt Quingentos rurſus ab Orbe datos:</l>
                  <l>Octogeſimus octavus mirabilis Annus</l>
                  <l>Ingruet, is ſecum triſtia Fataferet.</l>
                  <l>Si non hoc Anno, totus malus occidet Orbis:</l>
                  <l>Si non in nihilum terra, fretum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ruet:</l>
                  <l>Cuncta tamen mundi ſurſum ibunt at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> retrorſum.</l>
                  <l>Imperia, &amp; Luctus undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> grandis erit.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Which is thus done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by me.</p>
            <q>
               <l>From Chriſts Birth count a thouſand yeares compleate,</l>
               <l>And adde five hundred more with eighty eight:</l>
               <l>That yeare approaching! All men will affright:</l>
               <l>With woefull Terrours, which on them will light.</l>
               <l>If the whole World to ruine do not run,</l>
               <l>Or into nothing Land, and Seas be done:</l>
               <l>At leaſt, moſt Kingdomes topſy-turny turne:</l>
               <l>And men on all ſides grievouſly ſhall mourne.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113488:28"/>
            <p>I mention this <hi>Astrologicall</hi> Prediction, and theſe many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that happened this yeare, yet in the memory of man to the end, remembring what having already bin paſſed, we may in ſome meaſure conjecture of the like Accidents to happen in theſe our dayes. It is true, <hi>Saturne</hi> paſſeth through a ſigne once in two yeares and a halfe, ſo that in thirty yeares he runneth through the <hi>Zodiaque</hi> or the twelve Signes. And as often as he returneth to his place, <hi>Quadrate</hi> or oppoſite Aſpect, for the moſt part there happeneth extraordinary mutations in many parts of the World, according to the diverſe and various poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the other Planets to him, and amongſt themſelves, and the Ingreſſe of the <hi>Sun</hi> to the <hi>Cardinall</hi> poynts with Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if we looke in our <hi>Chronicles</hi> for the yeare 1593 (in which year <hi>Saturne</hi> was in <hi>Leo</hi> in <hi>Quadrate</hi> to <hi>Taurus</hi>) and ſo to the end of 1595 and upward, we ſhall finde the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell: The ſtory wherof is at large in Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> and others: And if we come neerer to our time, <hi>viz.</hi> In the years 1600 1601 and 1602 all which time <hi>Saturne</hi> was in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> we ſhall finde not onely them to rebell againe, but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> then landed, and had got footing in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but were with great loſſe to them driven out, with many other remarkable Paſſages worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory by all true ſpirited <hi>Engliſh</hi> men. I could much inlarge my ſelfe in theſe Hiſtoricall obſervations, and make them very fitly applicable to the <hi>Coeleſtiall</hi> Motions of the ſuperiours Starres and Planets, I ſuppoſe what hath already been ſpoke will ſuffice to informe any man of underſtanding, I do not ſay that becauſe there hath ſuch &amp; ſuch things happened to ſuch and ſuch places, when ſuch and ſuch Conjunctions and Aſpects of the Planets or Eclipſes have been, that the like muſt neceſſarily happen there againe at the like Congreſſe of the Heavenly bodyes, No. <hi>Ipſe Opifex Rerum voluit haec ordinatiſſima Coelicorpora, eſſe in Signa, tempora, dies &amp; Annos:</hi> God the Creator of all things willeth that theſe orderly Heavenly Bodyes ſhall be for Signes, times, dayes and yeares. <hi>Rideat igitur qui velit, &amp; cum ſuo detrimento, ſummo cum periculo conjuncto abiiciat, &amp; ſecurè &amp; ſuperbè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnat has qualescun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſignificationes Coeleſtes: Deus ſe derideri non patietur. Phryx non emandatur niſi plagie. Prudentiores faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113488:29"/> hinc haud dubie Divinitus admoneri ſe animadvertent, ut diſcant matura poenitentia &amp; vera converſione, &amp; ardenti pietate ad Deum confugere, &amp; antevertere, &amp; praecavere, Iram Dei horrendam adverſus noſtra multiplicia peccata, &amp; paenarum futurarum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> have ever beene moſt rebellious and treacherous to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and of late have moſt barbarouſly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanely murthered many thouſand innocent ſoules. Now they are at the height of their cruelty, and God is powring out his overflowing cuppe of wrath and vengeance upon them, and their adherents. <hi>Jamque ſecuris ad radicem poſita eſt, ut in fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſera arbor excidatur, &amp; in ignem conjiciatur.</hi> When God threatens a Nation, People or Family, he divers wayes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes them, before he ſends his Judgements upon them: ſometimes in the ſea, upon the land, in monſtrous births, in the fire by ſtrange apparitions, unuſuall tempeſts: ſometimes by Comets in blazing Starres, very often by Eclipſes of the Sun and Moone, and more uſually by the Configurations of the Planets amongſt themſelves and the <hi>Hebdomaticall</hi> Lunations, which if men would ſearch into, they might obſerve moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent matters to contemplate upon, and raiſe their thoughts to an exceeding height of Admiration of the moſt wonderfull workes of the omnipotent Creatour.</p>
            <p>I doe much wonder at the harſh unadviſed cenſure of many men: Divines and otherwiſe learned enough, that ſay nothing can be foreſeene by the ſtarres or their configuration: I muſt tell them Aſtrology is as ancient as our firſt Parents, (but the Antiquity of it doth not alone worke upon me) that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Univerſities, Princes, Sages, Philoſophers, from the firſt Infancie of the world to this very time, and will be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as long as the Sun Moone and Stars move in the Heavens. It depends upon as good grounds as any Art, It deales not by ſignes and effects, but by cauſes, whereof the motions, configura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and poſitions of the Heavenly Bodyes are grounded upon Mathematicall demonſtrations, and the propertyes or virtue of the Heavenly Influence, upon the obſervation or knowne experience of great learned men even from the beginning of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113488:29"/> world. And if the Divine will doe not counterchecke the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of nature, or the matter of thoſe Elementary Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies here beneath, be not unproportionable, and thereby unapt to receive their impreſſions: there is no reaſon why in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and phyſicall neceſſity, Aſtrologicall Predictions made according to Art ſhould not ſucceede and take effect. It deales not with rare contingents unknowne or undeterminate. But with theſe things which fall out for the moſt part, ſuch as are performed by Art and nature; It deales not with mans will ſimply and directly, but accidentally it doth; It deales with mens inclinations, diſpoſitions, temperature, affections and humours; It meddles not with miraculous workes, nor with fatall neceſſity, except ſome contingency be joyned with it, nor with Gods ſecrets: It is neceſſary for Phyſicke, Policie, Husbandrie, Navigation, Military Diſcipline, for health; It can yeeld reaſons which other Arts cannot, as in <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeares, <hi>Criticall</hi> dayes: Why children borne in the eighth month moſt part are not vitall. Of Tides: Why Cuſtomes, Rites, Manners, Lawes and Temperaments, be divers in people inhabiting in ſeverall Clymates: Why certaine Seaſons be turbulent; Why ſome yeares be dangerous. And many other things which may be read in that great Booke (of the moſt wiſe God) the Heavens; The Stars therein differing in glory and brightneſſe, one from another: but whoſe motions are moſt wonderfull Regular and Harmonious, which ſtares like ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall letters, ſome being capitalls and others of leſſe ſize, being as it were ſet together. A man endued with an apt Genius and Knowledge therein, may not onely ſpell, but in ſome reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meaſure reade the admirable Worke of God therein in their influentiall and ſecondary government of all ſublunary Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Faelices anima quibus hac cognoſcere primum,</l>
               <l>Inque Domus Superas ſcandere cura fuit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>On the other ſide I doe pitty the blinde ignorance of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (who thinke themſelves as learned as wiſe) that not knowing the motions of the Planets and ſtarres if they chance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113488:30"/> to ſee a ſtarre in the day time, doe wonder at the ſame, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves with ſome ſtrange conceit of ſome great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to enſue ſuch an Apparition: So it was in the yeare 1625, when a little before the death of King <hi>James,</hi> the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Planet <hi>Venus</hi> being occidentall of the Sun, and in her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſtance from him was thought to have beene a Comet or ſome <hi>nova ſtella,</hi> being Sunday in the Afternoone, the Moone and ſhe ſeemed to touch one another: or that as <hi>Kepler</hi> ſayes ſhe did <hi>quaſi haerere in ſiniſtro Cornu Lunae</hi> which I my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Yorke</hi> then with ſome others obſerved in the Weſt part of the Heavens.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe what great wonder and amazement there was in the yeare 1630 at that time when Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was borne, the ſame ſtarre <hi>Venus</hi> being then in great diſtance from the Sun, and orientall or riſing before him, was ſeen to goe before the Sun all day for the moſt part, I will ſet downe the words of <hi>Johannes Johnſtonius</hi> in his <hi>Thaumatagraphia, Capite</hi> 3. <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. Coeli Artic.</hi> 2. <hi>de ſtellarum luce &amp;c. Nona deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Junii hujus Anni, viſa una in</hi> Anglia <hi>ante meridiem, cum Gratia Deo propter nativitatem Principis</hi> Walliae <hi>agerentur, viſam eandem codem tempore Diepae in</hi> Gallia, <hi>a Gallis quibuſdam accepimus;</hi> That is, the ninth day of <hi>June</hi> in the forraigne account, (the 30 of <hi>May</hi> being Sunday in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> account) of this yeare one was ſeene in <hi>England</hi> before noone, when thanks were given to God (at <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>London</hi>) for the birth of the Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> And we received intelligence from certain <hi>French</hi> men, that the ſame Starre the ſame time was ſeen at <hi>Diep</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> But by leave of this Learned Gentleman I doe not accompt this a wonder, for it is uſuall with <hi>Venus</hi> once or twice in the yeare to ſhew her ſelfe in the day time, being in her greateſt diſtance from the Sun either when ſhe is orientall, or riſeth before the Sun, or occidentall and ſetteth after him, and this may be eaſily demonſtrated out of her Theory, If ſhe preſignified any thing ſhe was the <hi>prodromus</hi> of the miſeries that ſince have enſued to this Kingdome. And now at this very time the Royall party in ſome places as I am informed, flatter and promiſe themſelves ſtrange matters by reaſon this Starre
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113488:30"/> 
               <hi>Venus</hi> (none of them having ſo much Aſtronomy, as to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what ſhe is) appears ſo bright and glorious in the Weſt after Sun-ſetting; if ſhe betoken any thing, I ſuppoſe ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to our gallant Generall, and the reſt of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp; Souldiers now in the Weſt, as a bright lamp, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the darke, blinde corners of the Weſt, the unknown wayes of the enemy there and in <hi>Wales,</hi> to reduce that miſerable waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Country, which God be thanked is in a good forwardneſſe.</p>
            <p>I never obſerved or read that the ſimple appearance of any Star in the day time, foreſhewed any thing, except what <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomus Cardanus in lib.</hi> 14. <hi>de varietate rerum, cap.</hi> 70. mentions, whoſe words I will ſet down as they are there, <hi>Stellas quoque die ſereno bis vidiſſe Mediolani me memini cum tota Civitate; alteram ſplendidiſſimam Anno</hi> 1511. <hi>cum pulſi ſunt Galli; aliam Anno</hi> 1535. <hi>ſubobſcuram cum mortuus eſt Franciſcus Sfortia ſecundus: ſed &amp; tunc quod ſine filliis mortuus fuerit, mutatus eſt princeps, tranſiitque in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolum Imperatorem Civitatis Regnum, variato rerum ſtatu;</hi> that is, I remember my ſelf twice to have ſeen Stars in a cleer day at <hi>Millain,</hi> the whole City being ſpectators, one very bright <hi>Anno</hi> 1511. when the French were expulſed, and the other <hi>Anno</hi> 1535. ſomewhat obſcure or dark, when <hi>Francis Sfortia</hi> the ſecond dyed, but then he dyed without Sons, the Prince was changed, and the government of the City paſſed over to the Emperor <hi>Charles,</hi> with a various ſtate of affairs. I know not whether if God have ſo ordered the motion of the Stars, that Stars appearing in the day time ſhould foreſhew any thing; for my part I beleeve it not in that ſimple apparition; it is not proper for the Stars to ſhine or appear in the day: God made two great lights, the greater light to rule the day, and the leſſer to rule the night; he made alſo the Stars, and God ſet them in the Firmament to give light upon the earth, and to rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkneſſe, and God ſaw that it was good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>verſes.</hi> This I am ſure of, that they work by their influence inceſſantly day and night upon all creatures: Nay, in many places of Scripture, God would not tell us of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Stars upon the earth, and the creatures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113488:31"/> if they had no force, power and influence; in many places therein, they are called the Hoſt of Heaven, and the Armies of Heaven, therein amplifying the moſt wonderfull divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might of God, by the force, influence and energeticall operation of theſe glorious creatures; in ſome places, God expreſly diſtinguiſheth between the ſweet influence of the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iades</hi> (or the ſeven Stars) and the binding influence of <hi>Orion,</hi> under which two Conſtellations being of clean oppoſite na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and effect, God comprehends all the reſt of the Stars, and as it were by the figure of Locution, he puts the part for the whole, thereby manifeſtly giving us ſo much underſtanding, as to conceive all the other Stars of Heaven have their ſeveral particular vertues: God ſayes, <hi>He will hear the Heavens, and the Heavens ſhall hear the earth,</hi> Hoſea chap. 2. ver. 21. whereby we may be informed, that the fruits of the earth doe not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getate, nor have their dependance upon one, two or moe conſtellations, but upon the whole Heavens.</p>
            <p>We may read in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> chap. 33. ver. 13, 14. that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> amongſt his bleſſings upon the twelve Tribes, he bleſſed <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> in theſe words, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed of the Lord be his Land, for the precious things of Heaven, for the dew, and for the deep that coucheth beneth, and for the precious fruits brought forth by the Sun, and for the precious things put forth by the Moon:</hi> Where no man can deny but the vertues of the Heavens and the Stars are ſtirred up by the two Luminaries, the two great Lights, where the encreaſe of the earth is referred to the comfortable influence of the Sun and Moon, who are there ſaid to bring forth, put forth, or thruſt forth the fruits thereof, as the Original hath it: <hi>Quae quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Luna protrudit,</hi> they are not only thus declared in the Scriptures evidently to exerciſe their dominion in vegetable things alone, but they are further created for, and to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of men: Nay, there is no ſpeech nor language where their voyce is not heard; that is, there is no place in all the world, where they doe not operate and have influence.</p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 4. chap. ver. 19. that God in his exhortations to the Iſraelites, bids them that they ſhould not ſo lift up their eyes to Heaven, as that when they ſaw the Sun
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113488:31"/> and the Moon, and the Stars, even all the Hoſt of Heaven, they ſhould be driven to worſhip and ſerve them, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving divided them unto all Nations under the Heaven.</p>
            <p>By w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> diſtinction we are not to underſtand the light which they cauſe between day, and night, and the ſeaſons of the yeer; but we muſt underſtand the Miniſtery of the Stars to have a further conſtruction, nay, if there were no Stars in heaven, the Sun and Moon would be ſufficient to diſtinguiſh between night and day, Summer and Winter, and the other ſeaſons of the yeer; without queſtion the influence of the Sun, Moon and Stars, extends to the conſtitution and temperature of man; it is evident, that thoſe that are lunatick, whoſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per followes the courſe of the Moon, have their intermiſſions of their grievous fits as the Moon is wel irradiated, and on the contrary moſt grievouſly tormented as ſhe is afflicted, which is evident by the judgment of all Phyſitians; Nay, certainly we read in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. chap. ver. 32. that the children of <hi>Iſachar,</hi> by their skill and knowledge of times, could adviſe the Iſraelites in their actions; for the words are thus (and the children of <hi>Iſachar,</hi> which were men that had underſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to doe: And if ſo, then of the ſucceſſe, which is confirmed by innumerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in all Ages; and in Scripture we read (as I ſaid before) that the Stars in their courſes fought againſt <hi>Siſera,</hi> Judges chap. 5. ver. 20. By which it is evident, that they have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over men, &amp;c. Many Expoſitors underſtand this place of Scripture, that this fighting from Heaven was by hail, rain and Tempeſt, and true it is (ſaith the Author of <hi>Astrologomania (G. C.</hi> or <hi>George Carleton,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Landaffe,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Chichester,</hi> or the publiſher thereof, <hi>T. V.</hi> B. of D. or <hi>Thomas Vicars</hi> Batchelor of Divinity) fol. 105. That the Stars by their coſmicall riſing or ſetting are obſerved to further rain and tempeſt; for in the next words of the Text, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, the River <hi>Kiſon</hi> ſwept thtm away, whereby is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the inundation of the River cauſed by the hail and rain which fell from Heaven, whereby the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by the Tempeſt from heaven and drowned in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: This is evident by the Text.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:113488:32"/>
            <p>And becauſe the Scripture mentions ſo much in that place, and no more, and that many Tranſlators have ſo expounded that Text, muſt it be inferred thence, that the Stars have no other influence but in the cauſing of hail, rain, tempeſts, &amp;c. muſt the Stars be concluded from all other influence? all the Creatures of God are at his command, and are uſed as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to doe his will in the protection of his Church, and againſt his enemies; God moſt miraculouſly plagued <hi>Aegipt,</hi> with turning their waters into blood, and deſtroying their Fiſh, and ſent Frogs, Lice, Flyes, Murrain, boils and blains, hail, with Locuſts and darkneſſe among them, and the death of all their firſt born, and at laſt, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (purſuing the Iſraelites) with all his Hoſt, were drowned in the red ſea. Thus God wrought wonderfully, and beyond the courſe of nature: But in this place it is ſaid, the Stars in their courſes fought, &amp;c. under correction, beſides that expoſition; I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by courſes, the various motions, configurations, and divers Aſpects, the Sun, Moon, the reſt of the Planets and Stars have to one another, and amongſt themſelves; and by their fighting, &amp;c. I underſtand likewiſe, ſome notable configura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or poſition of the Stars or Planets, from whoſt influence (God having ſo appointed from the beginning) they cauſe wonderfull mutations in the world; and it is uſuall, when the ſuperiour Planets are in Conjunction, Quadrate or Oppoſite Aſpect to one another, very forcible; they doe not only cauſe rain, hail and tempeſts, &amp;c. but wars, murther, and great diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; other great changes have followed ſuch poſitions of thoſe Stars, as I could inſtance in all Ages, in innumerable, undeniable examples; I have named ſome already, I will only repeat the words of that moſt excellent man <hi>Henricus Rantzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius,</hi> a noble Dane, &amp;c. in his Examples of Aſtrologial Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon great Conjunctions, fol. 112. where he, amongſt other notable matters, ſayes, in that Book, which was the third Edition of it, and printed at <hi>Colen</hi> in the yeer 1585. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Domini</hi> 1583. <hi>Habuimus Conjunctiones, Planetarum ſedecim om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Piſcibus, inter quas fuit etiam Saturni &amp; Jovis, Anno</hi> 1584. <hi>Quatuordecim Conjunctiones in Ariete, &amp; Eclipſim Solis &amp; Lunae in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113488:32"/> Tauro, Anno Domini</hi> 1586. <hi>Conjunctiones etiam in Ariete tredecim &amp; unam in Tauro, Solis &amp; Mercurii: Deinde Anno Domini,</hi> 1588. <hi>Conjunctiones duodecim in diverſis ſignis: Has abſque dubio ſequentur nefaria Conſilia, ac facta, motus, ſeditiones, bella, caedes in Civitatibus Regnis &amp; Provincis, inaudita genera morborum, Pestis: Obitus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Regum, ac Dominorum, infinitae diſſentiones, ac novae diverſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes opinionum in Religione, ac denique ingentes calamitates in toto or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be terrarum, ut multi rerum coelestium periti opinantur, colligentes haec ex eventibus quae ſecutae ſunt praterlapſas Conjunctiones quas recenſui:</hi> That is, we have had in the yeer 1583. ſixteen Conjunctions of the Planets, al of them in <hi>Piſces,</hi> amongſt which was a Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter:</hi> In the yeer 1584. there was four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Conjunctions of the Planets in <hi>Aries,</hi> and the Sun and Moon Eclipſed ih <hi>Taurus:</hi> In the yeer 1586. there will be thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Conjunctions of the Planets in <hi>Aries,</hi> and one in <hi>Taurus</hi> of the Sun and <hi>Mercury,</hi> and afterwards in the yeer 1588. twelve Conjunctions of the Planets in divers Signs; without doubt after theſe (Conjunctions) will follow or ſucceed miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, villanous and wicked Counſels, and deteſtable Acts, commotions or troubles, ſeditions, wars, ſlaughters or kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Cities, Kingdoms and Provinces, unknown or unheard of diſeaſes, the plague, death of great Kings and Lords, Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diſſentions, and new diverſities of opinions in Religion, and to conclude, very great calamities in all the Countries of the world, as many skilfull men in coeleſtiall matters ſuppoſe, gathering theſe things from the events which are to follow theſe forepaſt Conjunctions now rehearſed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall hereunto adde ſome particular predictions out of the ſame <hi>Rantzovius,</hi> pag. 99. <hi>Friderici ſecundi imperatoris Astrologus ab eo interrogatus, cur tantum honoris Rudolpho, Haſpurgenſi Comiti pauperi in Aula ſua tunc verſanti, exhiberet, reſpondit, mortuis tuis filiis, quorum adhuc decem ſuperſunt, ipſe, &amp; posteri ejus ad tua Regna pervenient, Author Albertus Argentinenſis, quod exitus ipſe probavit. Nam Anno Christi</hi> 1273. <hi>Calend. Octob. Rudolphus a Germanis prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipibus Francofurti in Regem Romanum eligetur, cum Baſiliam obſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, &amp; hodierno adhuc die videmus Rudolphi poſteros Regnum Neopolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; Ducatum Austriae, &amp; Sueviae una cum Imperio &amp; Regno Neopolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no obtinere. Modernus nam Imperator Rudolphus ab eo nomen &amp; ditiones
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113488:33"/> haeditario jure accepit, &amp; Philippus Hiſpaniae Rex ex eodem natus Regnum Siculum &amp; Neoplitanum nactus eſt.</hi> That is, The Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger of the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, being asked by him, why he ſhowed ſo much reſpect to <hi>Rudolph</hi> the poor Earl of <hi>Habſpurg,</hi> then frequenting his Court: To whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer anſwered. Thy Sonnes being dead, of whom ten are yet living, He and his Poſterity ſhall attaine to thy Kingdoms; which the event proved, for in the yeer of Chriſt, 1273. the firſt of <hi>October, Rudolph</hi> beſieging of <hi>Baſill,</hi> was elected by the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> at <hi>Frankeford</hi> to be King of the <hi>Romans;</hi> and to this day we ſee the poſterity of <hi>Rudolph</hi> to enjoy the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> the Dukedoms of <hi>Austria</hi> and <hi>Suevia,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Empire and Kingdom of <hi>Naples:</hi> for the late Emperour <hi>Rudolphus,</hi> by hereditary right received from him, both his name, dominions and Empire, and <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> proceeding from him, obtained the Kingdom of <hi>Scicily</hi> and <hi>Naples:</hi> This <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond was elected 1212. he raigned 38. yeers, he dyed 1250. the Empire was void 22. yeers, though <hi>Conrade</hi> his Son, and <hi>Richard</hi> brother to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of <hi>England,</hi> who was Earl of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> were elected in the interim; and in the yeer 1273. this <hi>Rudolph</hi> was elected Emperour, and ſo continued ſeventeen yeers nine moneths and ſixteen dayes; it being ſixty yeeres before this prediction came to paſſe for ought I read to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>In pag. 97. in the ſame <hi>Rantzovius,</hi> thus I find; <hi>Magister Christianus Astrologus Pragenſis, Ladiſlaum Jagellonem Regem Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae per Sacerdotem praemonuit, ut mortem ſibi imminentem praecave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, quod multi Planetae conjungerentur, &amp; fieret Eclipſis Lunae ſub Terra; mortuus autem nihil ominus eſt eo Anno, qui fuit Annus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> 1434. <hi>Anno Aetatis</hi> 49. That is, Maſter <hi>Christian</hi> an Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger of <hi>Prague,</hi> admoniſhed <hi>Ladiſlaus Jagello</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> by his Prieſt, that he ſhould beware of imminent death, for that many Planets were conjoyned this yeer, and there would be an eclipſe of the Moon under the earth; notwithſtanding that premonition he dyed that yeer of our Lord, which was 1434. in the 49. yeer of his age.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113488:33"/>
            <p>In the ſame page, the next adjoyning obſervation is thus, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes Picus Mirandulae Comes, edidit Librum adverſus Astrologos, hi (inter quos fuerunt Bellantius Senenſis, Antonius Sirigatus Florenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; Angelus de Catastivis Carmelita) ut Artem veram ostende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, illum annum aetatis</hi> 33. <hi>non tranſgreſſurum predixerunt, ex dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione Aſcendentis ad Martem, quemadmodum hinc inde editis constat:</hi> that is, <hi>Joannes Picus</hi> Earl of <hi>Mirandula,</hi> publiſhed a Book againſt Aſtrologers: Theſe men (that is to ſay the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) amongſt whom were <hi>Bellantius</hi> of <hi>Sena, Antonius Sirigatus</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> and <hi>Angelus de Cataſtivis</hi> a <hi>Carmelite,</hi> that they might ſhew it [Aſtrology] to be a true Art, they foretold the ſaid <hi>Picus</hi> that he ſhould not eſcape the 33. yeer of his age, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the direction of the Aſcendant to the body of <hi>Mars,</hi> as it appears in the writings publiſhed upon this occaſion: I mention this the rather for that it is moſt appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt theſe three men were Aſtrologers, and by Aſtrology foretold to this <hi>Picus</hi> the time of his death, who flattering himſelfe with a falſe comfort, as if he could wrangle away Death by writing againſt Aſtrology, indeavouring to prove the Art vaine, his death concurring exactly with the time predicted, confirmed the ſame Art to be true, and more actually confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that which he had written againſt it, then if all the world beſides had conſpired to anſwer him.</p>
            <p>I have rehearſed theſe things, and been the larger upon them (though I could ſhew above one thouſand examples of rare obſervations Aſtrologicall,) and many of my owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment) to cure that <hi>Epiſcopomania,</hi> or, An examination of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydons</hi> Defence of Aſtrology. For would any man, but a man not well in his wits T. V.B. of D. pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Print, that the Aſtrologer foretelleth that is true, by the helpe of Satan; that Aſtrologicall predictions depend not upon naturall Cauſes; that Aſtrologicall predictions ſtand not by learning, but by ſome inſtinct; that Aſtrology con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth the fortunes onely of Fooles and wicked men; that the firſt Inventor of Aſtrology was the Divell; that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer attaineth not to his intended end in a Prediction without the helpe of Magicke; with many other abſurd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113488:34"/> Tenents. I will tell you a ſtory of himſelf, as he writes it in his Epiſtle Dedicatory, where he ſays thus; That thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions doe not always fall out jump and true as they would bear us in hand, but that either the Devil doth miſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, or that his Inſtrument doth miſtake his informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; this I am able to juſtifie and make good by a plain ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my ſelf when I was a child, and went to School at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leil,</hi> where I was born; there came an odde fellow about the Country, he was reputed a cunning man, and ſo called, for that he took upon him to tell fortunes; the fellow was dumb or at leaſt faigned himſelf ſpeechleſſe; but certain it was, he had an inſtinct or familiarity with ſome Spirit: This fellow being on a time in my Fathers houſe, there were ſome there more ſimply honeſt then religiouſly wiſe, made ſigns unto him, to ſhew what ſhould be my fortune, and another School-fellow's of mine that was then preſent: Whereupon this Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard having looked earneſtly upon us both, and pauſed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; For my School-fellow, he takes me a low ſtool and gets up upon it, with a book in his hand, and began to act after his faſhion, ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ying thereby that he ſhould be a Preacher: And for me, he took a pen and a ſcrole of paper, and made is though he would write, ſignifying thereby, that I ſhould be a Scrivener: Now ſo it fell out, that my School-fellow proved the Scrivener, and I prove the Preacher: By which it is plain to be ſeen, that either the Devil himſelf did miſſe, or his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument was miſtaken in his informations: Thus far he that proved a Preacher and Biſhop would have been, if the dumb man could have ſpoken, he would have told him ſo; A dumb man and tell fortunes! <hi>Riſum teneatis Amici!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What's all this to Aſtrology, or to Aſtrologicall predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to any man profeſſing Aſtrology, bounded within this definition? <hi>Aſtrologia eſt Doctrina, quae oſtendit vires ſtellarum, cognitas perpetua experientia, &amp; qualitates temperamenta, &amp; inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones in elementis &amp; corporibus hominum, ortas a Luce, &amp; motu ſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, quibus qualitatibus, temperamentis &amp; inclinationibus, reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſuae quaedam Actiones, niſi aut Divinitus, aut aliis cauſis fortiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus impediantur.</hi> For the more ſatisfaction in this matter,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113488:34"/> I referre you to my Almanacke for the laſt yeere 1645.</p>
            <p>I will only repeat what I mentioned in my Prognoſtication for the yeer 1643. (in ſome Aſtrologicall remembrances) and ſo cloſe up this Diſcourſe. In my Obſervations of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of the yeer 1640. amongſt others, I obſerved that <hi>Belliger &amp; iracundus Mars Anni hujus, Dominus, Vim irae &amp; Rabiei paſſim Capricornistis, &amp; toti ejus Quadrangulo tam Dirum in medium immittit, ut parum tranquilitatis illis remanſurum ſit, &amp; quod malum maxime Conjunctio Martis &amp; Saturni tribus vicibus hoc Anno in Aquario, Humano generi</hi> Hiſpalenſis <hi>authoritate, igne &amp; gladio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperabit,</hi> Roſea Jovis proſapia (that is, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prelats, &amp;c.) <hi>contentiones &amp; multa nova percipiet, &amp; collabentur deſiderabilia ipſorum, &amp; claudicabit ſanitus eorum:</hi> I could wiſh <hi>T. V.</hi> B. of D. would Engliſh this to the Epiſcopals and their party that cannot underſtand more then Engliſh; and in the ſame Revolution of that yeer, having found <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> to have been in Conjunction the fift of <hi>March,</hi> in five degrees 34. minutes of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> where <hi>Jupiter</hi> is cadent, and at the Suns entrance into <hi>Aries</hi> that yeer, <hi>Mars</hi> was newly ſeparated from <hi>Jupiter;</hi> I thought it a ſtrange Conjunction, and that no doubt it would produce as ſtrange matters concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſignified by <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> or the Jovialiſts and Martial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts: Whereupon ſearching ſome of the Maſters of Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, I found in <hi>Guido Bonatus,</hi> his <hi>Aſtronomia,</hi> 4. part, cap. 34. theſe very words; <hi>Si fueris ſuſpicatis utrum in Anno quem revoluit ſint futura praelia, ſeu diſſentiones &amp; unde excitentur &amp; a quibus; Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice illi rei ſecumdum modum quem tradiderunt nobis Antiqui, &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialiter ille reverendiſſimus predeceſſor noſter</hi> Albnumazar, <hi>qui fuit in Revolutionum Annorum ſcientia, etiam in omnibus aliis partibus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomiae proficuus, &amp; valde aſtutus &amp; audax; Eriges enim tunc fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guram ad</hi> Revolutionem Anni. <hi>&amp; conſtitue</hi> Aſcendens <hi>&amp; caeteras Domos, &amp;</hi> Planetas <hi>omnes in Domibus in quibus fuerint, &amp; aſpicè</hi> Martem, <hi>&amp; vide a quo ipſe ſeparetur, vel a quo ſit tunc ſeperatus; Dixit enim</hi> Albumazar, <hi>quoniam ille eſt qui miſit eum, &amp; qui exita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit</hi> Bellum, <hi>quamvis fuerit fortuna ille a quo ſeparatus fuerit</hi> Mars, <hi>etiam ſi fuerit</hi> Jupiter, <hi>tamen erit</hi> excitator Belli <hi>de perſonis, quae ſignificantur per</hi> Jovem, <hi>&amp; de potentioribus &amp; poſſibile erit, quod
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113488:35"/> ſit de genere</hi> Epiſcoporum <hi>&amp; ſimilium;</hi> Thus far <hi>Guido Bonaſus:</hi> I am ſure there was then ſuch a Conjunction, and that then <hi>Mars</hi> was newly ſeparated from <hi>Jupiter;</hi> there was then <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale;</hi> How at that time and ſince to this day, the effects have anſwered, let the world judge; and then fearing what ſince hath come to paſſe, in another place of that yeers obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, I made uſe of theſe words, <hi>Da pacem Domine in diebus noſtris, S. B. (Samuel Baker,</hi> then one of the Biſhops Chaplains and a Licenſer) expunged all this, and defaced it with a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leatur;</hi> I wonder how they love truth or peace, that will not ſuffer us to ſpeak of <hi>(praedict)</hi> or pray againſt War? was not there good ground of fears and jealouſies? If we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Eclipſes of the Sun and Moon 1639. and ſince that time, and the great Configurations of the Planets, ſuch as the Conjunction of the two Malignants, <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> three times in 1640. <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>June, Auguſt</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> and the Quadrate of them in the end of <hi>December.</hi> 1641. and the beginning of <hi>January</hi> 1642. and thereto adde the Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> the middle of <hi>May;</hi> as likewiſe the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> again in the ſame yeer, the 27. of <hi>May,</hi> with other great Conjunctions and Aſpects of the ſuperior Bodies, and compare the times, occurrences; we may eaſily ſee God forewarns us of his judgments by his <hi>Heavenly Militia,</hi> what bloody murthers, treaſons and trecheries, what unheard of cruelties have been acted in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the <hi>Rebels</hi> there, the powder-plotting-blood-thirſty Papiſts and their Adherents, perſons popiſhly affected? was there not great cauſe of Fears and Jealouſies? ſuch a fire is kindled, that it is even come to our own doors, threatning us with unnaturall inteſtine wars: This and much more I mentioned in that yeers Almanack, and thereto I refer you.</p>
            <p>I have but one note more to commend to the Iriſh, and I have it out of the above mentioned <hi>Rantzovius</hi> pag. 101 in theſe words; <hi>Richardus de rebus Hybernicis; attendendum eſt hoc loco, unum inſigniter diem Hypernicis infestum &amp; quaſi fatalem illux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe: Limericum die Martis Brittanni expugnabunt die enim Martis</hi> Guesfurdia <hi>fuit dedita, die Martis</hi> Waterfurdia <hi>ab obſeſſoribus oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupata
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113488:35"/> die Martis</hi> Dublinenſis <hi>Civitas armis oppreſſa:</hi> that is, <hi>Richard</hi> (or <hi>Richardſon</hi>) of the Affairs of <hi>Ireland;</hi> in this place [that is <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land]</hi> it is to be obſerved or liſtned unto, one day hath appeared famouſly hurtfull, and as it were, fatall to the Iriſh; the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains or Engliſhmen, expugned or won by aſſault <hi>Limerick</hi> upon a Tueſday; <hi>Weixford</hi> was yeelded up upon a Tueſday; <hi>Waterford</hi> was poſſeſſed by the Beſiegers upon a Tueſday; and the City of <hi>Dublin</hi> was oppreſſed by war upon a Tueſday; I know not why a Tueſday, yea every Tueſday throughout the yeer ſhould not be fatall to the Iriſh, for in this laſt Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I have made this Diſcourſe of; <hi>Mars</hi> (to whom Tueſday is appropriated, and therefore it is called <hi>Dies Martis</hi>) is moſt unfortunately placed: To every thing there is a time, and a time to every purpoſe under the Heaven, <hi>Eccleſs.</hi> 3.1. The Lord hath made all things for himſelf, yea even the wicked for the day of evil, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. That which hath been, is now, and that which is to be, hath already been, and God requireth that which is paſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.15. But enough at this time.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Ad Deum.</head>
               <l>Te nostrae moveant Deus quarelae,</l>
               <l>Et tristes gemitus, graveſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> luctus,</l>
               <l>Quos nobis varios ferunt, cient<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Exorti Stygio Lacu tumultus.</l>
               <l>Poenarum dedimus ſatis, ſuperque;</l>
               <l>Sat multi priere, ſat feroci,</l>
               <l>Bellonae licuit: Satis cruoris</l>
               <l>Hauſit Sacrilegi furor duelli,</l>
               <l>Quare diſidiis procul remotis,</l>
               <l>Optate redeat quietis aura:</l>
               <l>Hoc te ſupplici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, piiſque votis,</l>
               <l>Et multis lachrymis Deus rogemus.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>ILLVCens taVro MartIs ConIVnCtIo noVa nVnCIat hIbernIs ſatVrnI &amp; IVrgla Clto.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 M.</cell>
                        <cell>1000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5 C.</cell>
                        <cell>500.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 L.</cell>
                        <cell>100.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7 V.</cell>
                        <cell>35.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11 I.</cell>
                        <cell>11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1646.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Tueſday,</hi> 17. Martii 1645/6</date> being <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricks</hi> day the Saint of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
